<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Barneuels apology: or Holland mysterie· With marginall castigations.</title>
            <title>Mysteria Hollandica. English</title>
            <author>Oldenbarnevelt, Johan van, 1547-1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121064</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856253</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856253</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21782</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08477)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 930:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Barneuels apology: or Holland mysterie· With marginall castigations.</title>
                  <title>Mysteria Hollandica. English</title>
                  <author>Oldenbarnevelt, Johan van, 1547-1619.</author>
                  <author>Holderus, Petrus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[62] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by William Jones] for Thomas Thorp,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Mysteria Hollandica.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed by Robert Houlderus, i.e. Petrus Holderus, who also wrote the marginal reply.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ (-H4).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Barneuelts apologie, with marginall castigations.</note>
                  <note>Variant: quire A in another setting, with title page line 1 reading "BARNEVELTS" and dedication signed "Houlders".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oldenbarnevelt, Johan van, 1547-1619.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21782:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21782:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BARNEVELS APOLOGY: OR HOLLAND MYSTERIE.</p>
            <p>WITH MARGINALL CASTIGATIONS.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>NON PLVS</q>
               <p>Printed for <hi>Thomas Thorp.</hi> 1618.</p>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21782:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21782:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND WORTHY DAVID PAREVS, DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of Diuinitie, and chiefe Profeſſor of the <hi>ſame in the moſt famous and princely Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of</hi> Heidelberg, <hi>all tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of life.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS, that I dedicate to your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (right reuerend Doctor) is but ſmall in bulke and matter, but great in eſtimation and reſpect. And although the bulke appeareth of it ſelfe, and of it owne accord ſheweth it ſelfe to ech beholder: neither is the labour any other, then a Tranſlation out of the mother-tongue into Latine, and that almoſt word for word, without any ornament of ſtyle: yet Reſpect and Eſtimation doe adde an honour and grace to the bulke and labour: that euen therefore I hope the worke will be acceptable and pleaſant when you reade it. Acceptable ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, becauſe I offer it to you with all ſingular affection, and bending ſubmiſſion to your grauitie: Pleaſant certainly, for that therby you ſhall know the profitable proceeding of the ſincere <hi>Goſpel</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> as alſo the tottering and extreme ruine of the new vpſtart <hi>Arminians.</hi> For who among theſe was euer either a greater or bitterer enemie to our naturall Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, then this ſame, not ſo truly <hi>Olden-Barneuelt,</hi> as <hi>Berneuelt?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21782:3"/>
Hitherto verily we feared, and trembled at him, as oft as any mention came vnto vs of that lamentable and noyſome Schiſme to vs, out of <hi>Gelderland, Holland, Vtreicht, Ouer-Iſle, Frieſ-land,</hi> and the other vnited Prouinces: and wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood him among many to be the onely One, who durſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciouſly oppoſe himſelfe vnto the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the ſincere <hi>Word:</hi> the onely One, that, beyond the reſt, malepertly and malitiouſly affirmed the ſecular authoritie to be aboue the Eccleſiaſticall, and all and any aſſembly whatſoeuer, or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meeting together, at the leaſt of Doctors end Diuines: the onely One, that could and durſt repreſſe and keepe vnder Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> his Excellency, now Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (whom God graunt ſhortly to be Prince of all <hi>Holland</hi> alſo,) that hee ſhould not reſtraine from their courſe thoſe falſe brethren, falſe teachers, euen farre worſe then the Papiſts, and ſtoppe their peſtilent doctrine concerning <hi>Predeſtination</hi> and <hi>Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> that he ſhould not hinder by ſtrong-hand and warlike proweſſe all their conuenticles, nor compell them to come to more wholeſome Sermons, nor put to death thoſe babblers and praters, who ſeditiouſly often repeate, and cry out for <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of conſcience:</hi> Laſtly, the onely One, whom no man durſt offend, vnleſſe he himſelfe would grieuouſly offend, and at once ouerthrow himſelfe and all his fortune. And yet this Champion is now driuen to that ſtreight by the ſecret vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minings of ſome <hi>Proteſtants of ſincerer note,</hi> being diſrobed of his accuſtomed authoritie and deſire of bearing rule, rather then any abilitie at all, that he hath that way, that he muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſuiter to the meaner ſort, and craue their ayde, whom heretofore he domineered ouer. Reioyce, O worthy Doctor, and be glad O deere Brother: and ſo much the rather, for that not he alone is throwne downe, but becauſe he hath alſo drawne downe with him other of the chiefeſt followtrs and heretickes of that moſt deſperate <hi>Arminian</hi> ſect, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation long ſince ſlacketh not, and their deſtruction ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not. For <hi>Maurice</hi> the Prince of Orange his Excellency, who vouchſafeth neither to ſee nor ſpeak with him, and moſt reſolutely fighteth in defence of the Goſpel which wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:21782:3"/>
hath this yeere the firſt of Ianuary remoued all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians from the Senate at Nimmeghen, and hath put away the falſe Miniſters of the Word, and from Zutphen called foorth <hi>Damman,</hi> a man not eaſily to be ſeduced, and moſt conſtant for our true Doctrine; he hath called foorth others alſo from other places, appointing them to their former roomes, theſe deeds of his he afterward approued in the next <hi>Parliament of the Dutchie of Gelderland:</hi> So with the like courage and religious induſtrie, he depriued from all honour and authoritie, wherein he much excelled in the Councell of the States, the noble Lord <hi>Henry à Brinen,</hi> who had likewiſe oppoſed himſelfe to the Court of the Hage, and fauoured the Arminians: And ſo hath he brought to order all them of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Iſle;</hi> who, except <hi>Deuentrie,</hi> were already wholy bent to Arminianiſme: and eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Campen</hi> hee hath ſo daunted, who whilome ſince were vtter heretickes, making merchandize of the word of God, that ſcarce any one dare ſo much as whiſper againſt the ſound and ſincere doctrine of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as it hath beene taught by that moſt learned and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Doctor <hi>Iohn Caluin.</hi> So that we hope aſſuredly that thoſe Innouators of <hi>Campen,</hi> and falſe Miniſters of the Word, <hi>Thomas Goſwin, Iohn Schotler, Euerhard Voſculinlus, Aſſuerus Matthiſius,</hi> Satans owne excrements, who in the moneth of October in our conſecrated ſecular yeere 1617. publiſhed their diuelliſh <hi>Confeſſion</hi> (that they might pollute and defile the common ioy, almoſt through the whole Empire, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by giue occaſion to the Papiſts to write) againſt the Word of God, which endureth for euer: in which Confeſſion beſide other horrible matters,
<q>They haue branded euen the beſt and religious men.</q>
To alter a little from the words of our excellent Poet (happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as I ſuppoſe:) for I truſt that thou, the Muſes darling and the worlds delight, art ſtill of the ſame integritie, whereof thou wert, when we reaſoned ſo pleaſantly together of our mutuall ſtudies: and haſt not blemiſhed thy faire conditions with that ſame foule Goddeſſe of <hi>Daniel Henſius:</hi> who by reaſon of his in-bred want of audacitie concealed his name,
<pb facs="tcp:21782:4"/>
that publiſhed excellent Epigrams againſt them out of a city in Holland; and ſet himſelfe againſt a certaine ſhameleſſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell of thoſe or ſome other Arminians, called the <hi>Scales</hi> or Ballance. We hope (I ſay) that thoſe ſeruants of Hell ſhall ſhortly be reſtrained, driuen out, or by the helpe of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by ſtrong-hand to be of our opinion, and to make a <hi>better Confeſſion.</hi> The like we deſire alſo with our heart, to heare and vnderſtand concerning <hi>Greuenchouius, Bertius, Vorſtius. Grotius, Vtenbogartius, Slatius, Epiſcopius, Venator, Iohn Arnoldi,</hi> and other ſuch like fore-runners of Antichriſt, whoſe diſmall enterpriſes and horrid blaſphemies doe too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten trouble our eares and mindes. Bee glad and reioyce (my <hi>Pareus</hi>) that thoſe former ring-leaders being ſubdued, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt a Nationall Synod muſt be aſſembled: and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily by your aduice declared in your <hi>Irenicon.</hi> Will it not be an honour to thee? and a commoditie verily to vs all. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if the warlike prince <hi>Maurice</hi> ſit as Preſident therein, who will be able by his owne power and preſence ſo to terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the aduerſaries, and aboue all, if Sir <hi>Dudley Carleton</hi> Lid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for his Maieſtie of Great Brittaine, a moſt heauie friend to the Arminian-aſſes, be his Aſſiſtant, that no man dare vtter a word, that he knoweth will diſpleaſe them, and ſo will there be a moſt excellent peace, and great quiet in our inuiſible Church. Reioyce at leaſtwiſe, for that the firſt yeere of our <hi>New hundred</hi> after <hi>the yeere of Iubilee</hi> both begin proſperouſly. For as in the former yere we doe of right ſolemnize a Iubile, from the firſt reuolt of the renowned Doctor <hi>Martin Luther</hi> out of his irregular Cloiſter, and from the hard maiden-bed of the <hi>Auguſtines,</hi> to the pleaſing marriage of his chaſte <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine,</hi> and from his firſt diſputation at Wittenberg againſt <hi>Indulgences,</hi> which gaue the <hi>Pope</hi> (whom we by our law tearme <hi>Antichriſt</hi>) the firſt wound: ſo our poſteritie may one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres hence reioyce, for the vanquiſhing and ſubduing of <hi>Berneuelt, Brertius, Grotius,</hi> and the reſt, the firſt whereof was in a manner the very ſame among the Arminians, which that Biſhop of Rome was amongſt the Papiſts. Oh good Lord! what an occaſion haue we from hence to ſpeake and
<pb facs="tcp:21782:4"/>
fight againſt the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and hiſſing Popelings (for ſo I had rather name them, then by any other counterfeit name what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, leſt I alſo with that moſt learned <hi>Goclenius</hi> bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by I know not whom, ſome new ſcoffing <hi>Iohn Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> by a marueilous Metamorphoſis, to metempſychize and turne my ſelfe into a <hi>Swine</hi> or <hi>Giezi:</hi> though that alſo wil not goe ſcot-free, if I knew <hi>Raph</hi> aright?) What an occaſion haſt thou (my <hi>Pareus</hi>) againſt the Ieſuit <hi>Adam Contzius,</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximilian Sandie?</hi> Shake them vp roundly, I pray thee, and let them vnderſtand that we haue cauſe to <hi>reioyce,</hi> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate <hi>the hundred Yeere;</hi> but neither leiſure nor heart to weep. For elſe I ſhrewdly feare, leſt many gueſſe amiſſe of thee, (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the truth) and of thy abilitie, and of our whole cauſe: and fall away to that ſide, where we are aſſaulted with vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted weapons. Eſpecially ſeeing many of our curious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants ſo eagerly reade pratling <hi>Contius</hi> his <hi>Iubile of Iubilees,</hi> and the <hi>Thema ſeculare</hi> of ſaucie <hi>Sandie</hi> the Hollander, and confeſſe themſelues vnable to contradict them without one to inſtruct them: and moreouer, that there is ſmall efficacie in the <hi>Chronologie</hi> of the Euangelicall Iubilee, not very adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly publiſhed vnder the name of <hi>the Students of Nuiſs</hi> by our N. N. a man very well beloued to thee and mee: ſo that if it be ſifted indeed by the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> (whom yet I truſt are ſo buſied about the ouerthrow in Bohemia, that henceforth they neither liſt to write, nor ſpeake any thing againſt vs) we may much bluſh thereat: yea euen as much as we patiently did for your <hi>Syncretiſme,</hi> after it lighted into the hands and ſtyle of <hi>Moguntinus</hi> the Ieſuit. Which <hi>Iehouah</hi> the great God forbid, in whom I wiſh thee well to fare, and to take this my ſmall gift in good part. From my Studie at Francfurt this 27. of Iune. 1618.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours moſt bounden and affectionate with all his very ſoule,</hi> Robert Houlderus, <hi>Miniſter of the Word of God.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21782:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader of this Apologie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Berneueltius</hi> (gentle Reader) is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the chief of the vnited Factions in Holland. Now for that he hath ſome friends, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny enemies, and ſtandeth accuſed of many crimes, that he might aſſault his foes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his friends, hath publiſhed in print ſome few dayes ſince this <hi>Apologie</hi> in the vulgar tongue. But while by all meanes he endeuoureth therein to auoide the dangers of Charybdis, he is fallen into the barkings and vnluckie iawes of Scylla, being either too much mooued with the hatred of his aduerſaries, or too much blinded with the loue of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and of his friends: or certainly, that being now an old man of <hi>70.</hi> yeeres of age, and doating before his death, might fall as a more propice and fat ſacrifice at the Altar of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerpina.</hi> Farewell Reader, and if thou deſire to doe well thy ſelfe, let this old Dotard haue that fauour at thy hand, that he hath deſerued: yet I wiſh him in heauen, after he hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a ſound opinion and faith, from either of which he is very farre wide.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21782:5"/>
            <head>BARNEVELTS APOLOGIE: WITH MARGINALL CASTIGATIONS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable and mightie, my very good Lords:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING heretofore imployed my pen in writing for <note n="*">An inſinuating and deceitfull ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ordium: What will the narrati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on be?</note> the good of the Common-weale, ſo farre forth as cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie ſuffered mee: a neceſſitie ſeemed now to bee impoſed on mee, yet little further to trouble you in my priuate behalfe And that ſo much the rather, becauſe ſome there are who attempt the weakening of the State, and welfare of the Country, by my <note n="(b)">Let it bee a part of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders care not to credit him. For how can his depreſſion any way en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damage the State, whoſe deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on would haue purchaſed peace and ſecuritie to it?</note> affliction and depreſſion. Tis not long ſince a factious and ſeditious Booke came to light, which owes it birth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> it trimming &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this place, full fraught with iniuries and calumnies: which was afterward printed and ſent out to the world farre and wide, and euery where publiquely ſold. This Booke expreſſely and plainely without colours and diſſimulation depriues your Excellencies &amp; Honours of their proper right,<note n="(c)">Truth iuſtifies the contrarie but his beginning witneſſes in him a feare and diſtruſt of his cauſe.</note> and diſmounts from their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and dignities the Gouernours of our free-cities; among whom I am reckoned vnder the name of a Penſioner-greater. And indeed
<pb facs="tcp:21782:6"/>
fall who receiue Penſions and maintenance from the Countrie are to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alled Penſioners, I acknowledge ſuch may bee found in our Dominions; ſome great, ſome greater, ſome <note n="(c)">You are that grand-Penſioner, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd moſt pernicious, whatſoeuer our diſſimulation pretends.</note> grand-Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners: others little, leſſe, and petty ones. <note n="(d)">Your owne guiltie conſcience ſuggeſts this.</note> But I think this manner of ſpeaking may occaſionally beget confuſion, offence, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſuſpect both in the temporall, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall ſtate of what condition ſoeuer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f deſpight &amp; hatred tearme them Penſioners who ſtand for the immunities and franchiſes of our Countrey and free-States; <note n="(a)">This is that wherewith this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſt of men ſeckes to hurt moſt.</note> It followes, that theſe ſlanderers (if they be inueſted in the gouernement of the free-Cities of our Countrie or otherwiſe tied to your Highneſſes by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llegeance) doe oppugne their proper gouernement, and bond of their oath.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Holland</hi> and Weſt-<hi>Friſland</hi> the ſame men are Penſioners and Counſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ours, and for the moſt part are either Burgomaſters, or Aldermen, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-counſailours. In a word, this order of ſtipendaries liued in good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and eſtimation among them. And all this while <note n="(b)">Your ambition manifeſts in you greedy deſire to ingroſſe this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: but the world hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aken notice of your Foxes skinne, and makes you fall ſhort of it.</note> our Common-wealth was proſperouſly adminiſtred, both before, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as alſo in the time of warre, and is ſo ſtill, the ſame Gouernours ſitting at the helme. So that it is not a little to bee maruelled at, why theſe cauillers ſeeke to drawe the gouernement thereof into diſgrace and enuie, by their libelling and carping bookes.</p>
            <p>As for my particular place, and function, it was heretofore many yeeres before the warre in good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute and credit with the <note n="(c)">Selfe-loue makes you ouerpriſe your ſelfe. You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould rather haue ſaid, with drudges and Kitchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyes.</note> Gentrie, Nobilitie, and free-Cities of <hi>Holland</hi> and Weſt-<hi>Friſland:</hi> yea and the very Princes of the Countrey, and the Gouernours thereof; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies retained the name of <note n="(d)">Could you chalenge the name of Aduocate-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral before the warres? You are taken in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. For if this be ſo, you were Aduocate in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adling cloutes, or when you could not ſit on a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unch of Straw.</note> Aduocate general, which it pleaſed the Gentrie &amp; Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who appeared perſonally in our Countries Parliaments, to vſe as a ſet Officer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21782:6"/>
               <note n="(a)">Open your minde briefely, and boldly ſay, I was α and ω, the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginning, and the ending, the firſt and the laſt, of honourable and mighty States, of all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cels, and Aſſemblies, of all Sta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutes and Decrees. Alter your ſtile and wee will ſubſcribe you wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the originall of all diſaſters an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> calamities, eſpecially ſuch as hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pened vpon the rent and ſchiſme in the renewed, and reformed reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion, whoſe ſworne enemy wee a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uow you.</note> The prerogatiue of my Office then conſiſts chiefely in this: <hi>viz.</hi> to haue a prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in all matters, and to defend the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignties and rights of your Honors and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies: and the immunities of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: to haue the care of calling your pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Aſſemblies: in them to haue a voice in all buſineſſes, to take charge of Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances, and Petitions tendred vnto you, and to exhibite them at time conuenient: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and deliberate with the Nobles concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, and all other things propounded in theſe meetings. That being done, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the verdict paſſed either by ioynt conſent, or at leaſt pluralitie of voices, to be your verdict: and to ſtrengthen the ſame with allegations and reaſons as ſhould be moſt fit. Afterward, to demand the ſuffrages of free-Cities, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude by moſt voices: and, laſtly to imploy my vtmoſt abilitie, that what then was decreed, might be put in execution.</p>
            <p>This Office was vacant both in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland, anno</hi> 1584 where my Predeceſſor <hi>Paul Buys</hi> renounced and gaue it ouer. Now as I with others of the Nobilitie, and free-Cities of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> firſt went Embaſſadour to the Queene of <hi>England, anno</hi> 1585: So was the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Maſter <hi>Paul Buys</hi> ſent Embaſſadour thither by the States of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trickes</hi> That very yeere after my returne out of England (two ſeuerall Treaties beeing diſpatched there with the Queenes Maieſties Commiſſaries) I <note n="(a)">Your perſwaſions ſhall not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs to beleeue you.</note> manifeſted my zeale and affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my beſt deſeruing Lord and Maſter, the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> of famous memory. <note n="(b)">Now your policie ſhroudes it<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe in a gowne, which afterward wee ſhall ſee changed into a ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Iacket.</note> I dealt earneſtly, that the Gouernment of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland</hi> might be deliuered vp to him by the worthy Lords the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter:</hi> becauſe my thoughts told mee, that hee (by reaſon of a cuſtome receiued in <hi>Brabant,</hi> and a rumour, which I tooke notice of in England) would make claime to it. The matter was determined of by the conſent of the <hi>maior</hi> part, though after a canuaſe and much adoe.</p>
            <p>Towards the end of the yeere 1585. the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> entered into
<pb facs="tcp:21782:7"/>
theſe Regions, &amp; was euery where <note n="(c)">Whether doe you command <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eere the perſon entertained, or his entertainers?</note> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with great triumph, and at the <hi>Haighe</hi> about the beginning of the yeere 1586. or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained generall Gouernour with abſolute power, and authoritie. Now was Maſter <hi>Paul Buys</hi> admitted into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell in behalfe of the Prouince of <hi>Vtricke.</hi> Hereupon it ſeemed good to the Gentlemen, Nobles, and free-Cities of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue the Office of Aduocate-generall of the countrey. And Legates vvere ſent by the Nobles and free-cities to the Gouernours thereof, as alſo <note n="(d)">A matter of import no doubt, Which huff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>puft lungs thus belches out</note> priuately to my ſelfe, to proffer that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to mee, and exempt and acquite mee of my bounden ſeruice to the Gouernours of <hi>Rotterdam.</hi> I <note n="(a)">Now for a Momus: if this mans brest had a Latice window in it.</note> vrged then many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that they would hold mee excuſed. As firſt, want of money, which was required in a man of that place: then my deſire to eſchew aemulation: and diuers other cauſes: but no excuſe might ſerue the turne. Thus was I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to aduenture my ſhoulder vnder a<note n="(b)">This the language of diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, with whom a ſcape paſſes for curra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vnder the name of coughing</note> burden vnſought for. Neuertheleſſe, I put in two cautions. Firſt <note n="(c)">This vnderhand-packing is then moſt treacherous, when it is couered with the cloke of honeſtie. You ſweat much in labouring to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the ſuſpicion of cloſe league and intelligence betwixt your ſelfe and the Spaniard: but credulitie it ſelfe will not credit you.</note> in caſe conſultation were had of returning theſe Regions to the Spaniard (which I feared for many weighty cauſes) that then I would bee diſcharged of this Office <hi>ipſo facto.</hi> Secondly <note n="(d)">Herein I aſſent to you, though the reaſons which you alledge, will not abide the triall. For put caſe none of the feared inconueniences followed vpon your abſence; yet would not you be wonne to leaue the Countrey: vnleſſe you might hope to fill your pouch with pelfe, and bribes, and turne your abſence to your priuate commoditie.</note> that I might be ſent no where out of the Prouince without my owne free conſent; that by this means nothing might ſcape my knowledge, and I might in perſon withſtand thoſe, who haply would embrace all aduantages, which my abſence promiſed, in infringing our cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomarie proceedings: the rule whereof was to be ſought for at my hands.</p>
            <p>I vndertooke this weight in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of March <hi>Anno</hi> 
               <note n="(e)">Then the warre was not afoot. How then durſt you broach a lye before? But this is no vncouth matter with you, who in theſe few ſheetes haue tranſgreſſed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bounds, which truth preſcribed not fewer then a hundred times which euery attentiue Reader m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerue, and conſider the Dutc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prouerbe which ſayes, <hi>Shew m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a lier, I'le ſhew you a Theefe.</hi>
               </note> 1586. and I found all former cuſtomes, and orders inuerted. All autoritie was transferred vpon the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter. Graue Maurice,</hi> and <hi>Count Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> receiued inſtructions for their gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:21782:7"/>
of the foreſaid Earle. At <hi>Zeland</hi> they moued queſtions touching the extent of their borders &amp; portions, to the great annoiance of the <hi>Hollander,</hi> and Weſt-<hi>Friſlander.</hi> The <note n="(f)">Perſiſt in your lying, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerate all things: that you ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lay a ſure foundation of your brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariſme, and vaine-glory, for yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue the tricke of it.</note> Companies of the Grand-Prouinciall Aſſemblies, the Maſters of Accounts, and Magiſtrates of the <hi>Haighe</hi> were ſo animated againſt the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> that both by words and writing they called into doubt, whether the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> had ſo much autoritie left them, as might warrant them to enioine the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the tribute and contributions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. Many alſo of the Gouernours of the free cities were ſiniſterly affected towards the State, by reaſon of the detaining of certaine goods, and ſome proceedings intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. <note n="(a)">Hitherto you did but ſpatter now you beginne to ſpue, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the poiſon which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay in your i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fected ſtomacke, that with noiſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> belches you diſgorge vpon the inn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cent Miniſters of Gods Word whoſe ſhoo-latchets you are v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy to tie. But looke to you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſelfe, you muſt ſwallow down on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againe theſe stinking gobbets.</note> Many of the Preachers would no longer now acknowledge their fealty to the States: and they demanded of the Earle of <hi>Leicester,</hi> without the priuitie of the States, the indiction of a <note n="(b)">The Readers owne obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on may tell him, where this Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minian <hi>Berneuell</hi> his ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wrings him. That hee may m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſt and let the future Synode or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dained for the publike good, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drawes the name of a Synode, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the authors thereof, into enuie. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is a cuſtomarie thing for men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hate the light, which worke wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedneſſe: and they who couert diſperſe and ſcatter abroad v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> truths, come in place where tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is vnmasked againſt their wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But the Arminians were now a good while ſince deſperately vncurable: concerni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whom, that may be truely ſpoken, which is ſtamped in pieces of money, and other coin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vſed at the <hi>Haighe, What need ſpectacles when a man will not ſee?</hi>
               </note> Synode Nationall, as they call it. The garriſons had bound themſelues by oath to the ſaid Earle. The promiſcuous multitude was an enemie moſt what to the States. And not long after the cities of <hi>Graues,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>endloe</hi> and others were poſſeſſed by the Spaniard. <hi>Nimeghe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> was violently aſſaulted: there was great hurly-burly, and diſorder about contributions, and the procuring of money. For monies lent wee were neceſſited yearely to pay twelue pound in the hundred for vſe, &amp; two pound more for brocage. The charges were greater by many degrees then our reuenewes. The
<pb facs="tcp:21782:8"/>
Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> eſtabliſhed many Edicts, in which he vſed his owne name and ſeale. The ſhipping not onely of forrainers, but euen of neighbour Kingdomes and Prouinces, was by publique decrees ſubiect to his power: heere I ſtaggered in my purpoſes, and was, not without iuſt cauſe, doubtfull what to doe: but the Lord ſtrengthened, and enabled me to attempt the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt meanes for the calming of theſe ſtormes, whereinto theſe ſtraites had caſt vs.</p>
            <p>Many enormities were obſerued by certaine of the moſt principall men (in which number was the Lord Gouernour <hi>Vander Myle,</hi> of famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, a man at that time beſt ſeene in the Countries affairs) as alſo by ſome of the Nobles, and ſome of the free-Cities: and it was found out, that whatſoeuer was done tended hitherto, that <note n="(a)">This was that which you lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for, that you might fill your bagge, and with open violence op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the innocent, and skulke in all theſe miſchiefes vvith impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</note> warre would ſuddenly enſue. Some few daies after, an innouation beganne at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricke.</hi> Many an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and honeſt Patriots of eminent place were both thruſt out of their Offices and dignities, as alſo out of the Citie. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement was allotted to ſtrangers. <hi>Bellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> of <hi>Flanders</hi> was created Preſident; <hi>Agileus</hi> of <hi>Brabant</hi> generall Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator: Praetors, Conſuls, Queſtors were all Brabanders.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Paul Buys</hi> was caſt into priſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(b)">Let men of diſcretion, and ſuch as are acquainted in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the buſineſſe, pauſe heere awhile. For if theſe were to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a reaſon of your vvords: you would ſlip the collar.</note> The Reformation inſtituted in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> his temple, which <note n="(c)">Was not the deſcription ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of worth your paines? But you purpoſely omit it, that you may more ſecurely packe, and ſhuffle in your vntruth.</note> at firſt was accepted of by the moſt principall men, ſeemed now not ſound and ſincere enough, &amp; therefore was altered. And yet, this was not ſufficient. There was further in the ſaid place an Act made by the Common-Counſellers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they deliuered vp the Prouince of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricke</hi> to be abſolutely commanded by the Queene <note n="(d)">Heere I could wiſh, that that royall Prince liued: or if not ſo, yet now haled you, hanging backe, with her virgin hands, before <hi>Radamanthus</hi> his iudgement ſeat. As ſure as what is moſt ſure, if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one, or other of theſe two things were gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, you were vtterly vndone.</note> of <hi>England</hi> at her pleaſure, without prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any conditions. This meane while the <note n="(e)">Doe you not couertly accuſe theſe noble orders to bee faulty? Heere now I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale from the Readers to the pronouncers of iudgement: yet by way of informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not accuſation, leaſt I ieopard his head: and thus much he ſhall be beholding to me.</note> States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland</hi> vſed
<pb facs="tcp:21782:8"/>
their vtmoſt endeuours for the performance of thoſe things, which they granted &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the Earle. All theſe things notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, they exhibited remonſtrances, and complaints about the redreſſing of miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours: but they obtained nothing but promiſes and faire words.</p>
            <p>The Earle departing from the Haigh, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched his campe about <hi>Doesburg</hi> and <hi>Sutphen.</hi> The plots of <hi>Iames Reingout,</hi> and <hi>Stephen Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> are heere <note n="(a)">And let mee tell you, ſo are yours, least perhaps you flatter your ſelfe too much.</note> diſcouered, and it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Reingouts</hi> papers, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricke</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vp by his priuitie, and perſwaſion: and that it vvas therefore conuenient, that this olde leauen ſhould be purged out there. Decrees are publiſhed of an intended Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Synod.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(b)">That is, Aduocate <hi>Berne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,</hi> their mouth, and eares, an enimie to the ancient reformed religion, who is not worthie to enioy the light of the Sunne, or tread vpon the earth.</note> The generall States made a ſcruple to approue theſe without the conſent of the States of the Prouinces, euery one ſeuerally for their owne parts, by whom they vvere deputed Delegates. Which act of theirs of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended very many, and made themſelues o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious. Writings, aſſaults, and publique ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Churches were made againſt them. The <note n="(c)">What an indignitie is this, that theſe famous Orders ſhould bee thus ſlandered? that they ſhould bee ranked in the number of double-harted baſelings, which pretend one thing, and intend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</note> States of <hi>Holland</hi> temporized heere, and thought they might doe well to accept thoſe decrees for a time: prouided, the ſtates, Nobles, and each free City ſhould retaine in the <hi>Interim</hi> their power, and <note n="(d)">Buzzing whiſperer, tell mee whence had they this power and right? Was your head or the three-headed <hi>Cerberus</hi> the mint of it, or both? I know you alleage <hi>Brentius</hi> here for confirmation of your purpoſe: But I referre you to that light of our reformed Church, Maſter <hi>Caluin,</hi> who in his Booke of Inſtit. Chap. <hi>12.</hi> ſ. <hi>8.</hi> and ſo forward, is of our ſide, and diuinely teacheth, that the Eccleſiaſticall authoritie of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, and the power of the ſecular Magiſtrate are <hi>2.</hi> things, ſo diſioyned, that they are incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible in the ſame perſon or State: If you reiect <hi>Caluin,</hi> you are an Heretick, and worthie to bee burned.</note> right in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and diſplacing the Miniſters of the Church. The Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and Councel of the States gaue out acts approuing this. The States complained of <note n="(e)">Dare you yet againe twitte our Preachers as factious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? the Miniſters of Gods word? But you blabber out theſe things, eyther to ſowe ſedition in <hi>Holland,</hi> or to help the growth of it now already ſowne. But command your tongue ſilence rather, for all Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers, if indeede and truely Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers, are louers of Peace. As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or your Arminians, they are the Diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls inſtruments, and the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owes to blow the fire of contention.</note> factious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons:
<pb facs="tcp:21782:9"/>
it was coldely and doubtfully anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that they were to bee conſtrained to vſe another manner of preaching. The States <note n="(a)">So will I, and thoſe of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reformed Religion for your baniſhment; with this prouiſo, that you may bee carried to the <hi>black-Iſlands,</hi> where you may not haue the benefit of the light, nor ſtuffe more Papers with lies &amp; ſlanders.</note> importuned <hi>Reingouts</hi> baniſhment. This was determined in the Earls preſence: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Reingout</hi> at his parting, burſt out into theſe words; <hi>I haue made ſhipwracke of my au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and power. Reingout</hi> then (who was ſo religious, that he would not ſuffer man or maid in his houſe, that receiued not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion) <note n="(b)">We ſhall ſhortly heare the like newes of you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For whatſoeuer you ſay, the Spaniard is a great Man in your Bookes, and you are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy halfe a Papiſt, and more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous then a profeſſed Papiſt.</note> reuolted to the Spaniard, and died a Papiſt. The Earle of <hi>Leicester,</hi> after he was reſolued to goe for <hi>England,</hi> dealt priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly himſelfe in <hi>Holland</hi> with<note n="(c)">Noble Prince, can you heare theſe things and endure them? Perceiue you not the vnderminings of this ſubtile Foxe? Tis a calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niation and a ſlander againſt your Excellency, let him ſmart for it.</note> 
               <hi>Graue-Morris,</hi> that he would depart with him. I letted the ſucceſſe of this intendment, which in a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and ful Aſſembly was caſt in my teeth: and the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> after the hearing of my allegations, ſaid, hee was not now to learne, what theſe things aimed at. The Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> at his departure, left behind him two Acts concerning the proceedings of Prouincial affaires. After this Earles death, <hi>Stanly</hi> and <hi>Yorke</hi> (for not onely ambitious, turbulent, and beggerly fellowes, but trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours alſo haue their place in factions) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyally ſurrendered <hi>Deuenter,</hi> the holde of <hi>Sutphen</hi> to the Spaniard, as afterward <hi>Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was betraied by <hi>Paton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lords Generall of the States about the beginning of February by their letters did repreſent their complaint to the Queen, and the Earle concerning <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> of the Acts of both the ſaid Earle and his follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, and retainers. Then did you enlarge the authority of <hi>Graue-Maurice,</hi> and of the Count, making the former <note n="(d)">
                  <p>Do you not enuie his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, this Title? The more iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſort deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry your windings and contriuals: but your worth moſt excellent Prince ſecures you. For howbeit moſt pages of this your aduerſaries Booke leuell at your perſon and authoritie, yet it is to no purpoſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Son dard, ſans faire coup, il à lancè en vain.</l>
                     <l>Voſtre airain enrouè le pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerà ſoudain.</l>
                     <l>Againſt your woundleſs breſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> he bolts his dart in vaine:</l>
                     <l>Your clattering Brigandine ſtill beates it back againe.</l>
                  </q>
               </note> gouernor, and the other, generall Lieutenant; allowing them 80 companies of ſouldiers for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="tcp:21782:9"/>
of the ſaid Prouinces. And whereas the ſaid Earle purpoſed himſelfe to returne hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto vs in perſon, hee ſent before him his Secretarie, whoſe wiles and inſtructions were diſcouered, and defeated by my paines and induſtry.</p>
            <p>The Earle returnes, looſes <hi>Sluſe,</hi> the comminaltie of <hi>Middleborough,</hi> makes an vprore in the Abbey. The Earle cheriſheth their ſedition, and goes on forward to <hi>Dorth:</hi> ſom were ſent thither to him by the States, to craue other ordinances. In the meane while I was certified, that he had a commiſſion, to propound a treatie to make peace with the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard. That doe I then publiſh to the world: he had notice hereof: he <note n="(a)">Who can credit this? are you, with whome lying is familiar and ordinary, a telle-truth, and the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> a periurd lier? but by this time your voice hath rung ouer all Hell. Aeacus openeth the gate to you, you are led to iudgement, vnleſſe haply <hi>Great Brittaines</hi> King ſeize on you by the way, and hauing firſt cauſed that hand and tongue to bee cut out (which ſo malapertly diſgraces the Earle euen after his death, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily ſeekes to gall Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> and King <hi>Iames</hi>) after, when you are thus dreſſed turne you ouer to the other vnrelen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Iudge.</note> ſweares, forſweares, calles God and man to witneſſe, and vtterly denieth that hee had any ſuch charge. He hies him to the <hi>Haigh,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands certaine troupes of horſemen to goe to <hi>Sluſe</hi> vpon <hi>Moſe,</hi> and the port <hi>Delfe.</hi> The Burgomaſters, <hi>VVingarden</hi> (who was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Preſident) and with him <hi>Caſenbroodt,</hi> came to me by night, and aduertiſed me, that the Earle made a ſearch for mee, with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to conuey mee into <hi>England.</hi> I betooke my ſelfe to <hi>Delfe</hi> by night, and there I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that it was rumoured in <hi>Zeland,</hi> that <hi>Graue-Maurice,</hi> my ſelf, and ſome others of the States, ſhould bee certainely ſent into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſultation was had concerning theſe matters at <hi>Delfe,</hi> and it was agreed vpon, that Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> ſhould depart the next daie from the <hi>Haigh,</hi> which was accordingly performed. Maſter <hi>Valke,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Looſen</hi> came that ſelfe ſame day about noone-tide to <hi>Delfe,</hi> to treat with mee there about Prince <note n="(b)">Belike then <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> was in his nonage, and you were his Guardian and ouerſeer.</note> 
               <hi>Maurice</hi> his returne, but all in vaine.</p>
            <p>The Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> after he vnderſtood that Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> and Count <hi>Hohenlo</hi> mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered ſouldiers, departed to <hi>Vtrick,</hi> and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,
<pb facs="tcp:21782:10"/>
after he had diſpatched all things there according to his wiſh, to bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto his ſubiection the Church, by which name hee meant <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> But his purpoſes were detected, and preuented by the fidelity of the true hearted Hollander, Conſul &amp; Captaine <hi>Peter Boom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore hee went forward to <hi>Horne,</hi> in hope to ſeize vpon <hi>Capell</hi> which had confederated it ſelf with <hi>Anchuſen:</hi> but the good Patriots hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntelligence of his intent, denied his entrance into the city.</p>
            <p>While the Earle lingers in <hi>North-Holland,</hi> two heauie meſſages were brought to him: firſt, that his plots thriued not in the good city of <hi>Leiden,</hi> and that the remnant there had eſcaped by flight; &amp; preſently after, that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Coſmo,</hi> Captaine <hi>Maud,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iames Valmaer,</hi> Elders of the Church, were puniſht w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> death for their atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted treaſon. A ſecond thing w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> appald him, was this, becauſe his interceſſion, that treatie of Peace might not be offered the States, was cried out on in England, and he was commanded the ſecond time to propound the matter either himſelfe, or ſome Engliſh man for him. After he had receiued theſe tidings, he ſaid, <hi>It was now high time for him to</hi> 
               <note n="(a)">
                  <p>Let his example be your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident: This counſell I giue you vnasked. <hi>Charitie wiſhes to giue counſell where it is not askt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Haſten your courſe, but beware you take <hi>Dort</hi> in your way. You may conueniently exchange <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdam</hi> for <hi>Antwerpe;</hi> or if you be pleaſed to viſite <hi>Vtricke,</hi> and your clients there, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>y make a ſhort cut to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ukes wood, being guarded with the Arminian brethren: and that you may trauell with more ſafety, and not bee intercepted by the ſpies and warders (<hi>Leiden</hi> and <hi>Vtricke</hi> threaten no danger, but their borders very much) ſend before you <hi>Bertius,</hi> and <hi>Vtenbogartie,</hi> like two defenſiue dogges to ſcoure the way, and forewarne ſuch as lie in wait. Afterward flye into Spaine, and die a Papiſt. But heare, which I had well-nigh forgotten, that way is dangerous too, and may tumble you into Purgatorie: and ſend before you euen hither too thoſe your two companions, that you may ſafely paſſe, while the Porter of the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie buſies himſelfe with them.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>looke to his head.</hi> Wherefore ſuddenly, yet not without ſuſpicion, he iourneyed firſt to <hi>Vtricke,</hi> from thence to <hi>Delfe,</hi> then to <hi>Fluſhing;</hi> and laſtly from <hi>Fluſhing</hi> he betooke himſelfe into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While the Earle ſtayed in <hi>North-Holland,</hi> your Highneſſes and Honours aſſembled at <hi>Harleme,</hi> that you might be in more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for all aſſayes. There then the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie of <hi>Vtricke,</hi> which conſiſted of <note n="(b)">If you were bound to proue this, you would ſweat for it.</note> ſtrangers, were inſtant with many, both by
<pb facs="tcp:21782:10"/>
writings, and by diuers of their <note n="(a)">You would be cleane ſpoiled if you ſhould not make Preachers to haue a finger ſtill in all muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: ſo that you were borne as it may ſeeme, to checke and taunt them.</note> Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, as alſo by word of mouth, that they would perſwade your Highneſſes, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to enlarge the Earle of <hi>Leicesters</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: but their endeauours were ſtoutly withſtood. I cannot expreſſe in writing (my good Lords) in <note n="(b)">This is Lord-like indeed. The God of warre himſelfe dare not open his mouth to parallell his ſtrength with yours.</note> how great dangers, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, and paine I paſſed thoſe two yeares: with what courage and alacritie moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous diſtreſſes were vanquiſhed, and the countrey defended.</p>
            <p>As <note n="*">What reckoning, trowe we, do you make of your oath: who are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to diſcouer ſecrets. Know you not the old Prouerbe, A ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant must not vtter all he knows: but a deſire to couer your ſelfe, and the hatred of your aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry makes you forget your ſelfe.</note> concerning the Peace, (which was firſt propounded by the Earle, and afterward deſired of the Queene of <hi>England</hi> by Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours extraordinarie) it appeared, the matter was commenced in an aſſembly of of the generall States amongſt thoſe, who were deputed thereto by the Prouinces, and alſo amongſt the particular members, and Cities of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland:</hi> and likewiſe amongſt the <note n="*">
                  <hi>You are alwaies bitter againſt the Preachers:</hi> Le vent nourrit le feu; &amp; en ſoufflan l'allume. The ſame winde cheriſheth the fire while it is yong, and after kindles, and brings it to its ſtrength and height.</note> Preachers, and ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and brought to that paſſe, that the Queene of happy memories demand ſhould be ſatisfied. Wherefore it was neceſſarie to vſe ſingular dexteritie, labour, and paines to reconcile the diſſentions and ſchiſmes of the Prouinces (among whom the <hi>Friſlanders</hi> were ſo <note n="(c)">
                  <p>You are an enemie to Peace; are you not? But if you had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, what euen the chiefeſt and beſt in <hi>Friſland</hi> haue, you would be an enemie and hater of warre.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Non ſa quae val'la pace, &amp; non l'eſtima,</l>
                     <l>Chi prouato non a la guerra prima.</l>
                     <l>They know not how peace to preferre,</l>
                     <l>Who neuer felt th' extremitie of warre.</l>
                  </q>
               </note> deſirous of peace, that there Commiſſioners were not onely inioined to aſſent to, but further to repaire to the place appointed for the making vp thereof) that this once effected, Embaſſadours might be ſent into England vnto the Queen, who might lay before her ſundry difficulties and conſiderations of import, which withſtood this buſineſſe, which ſhe according to her excellent wiſedome ſhould ponder of: and whoſe determination concerning the ſame, the ſaid Embaſſadours ſhould bring backe
<pb facs="tcp:21782:11"/>
vnto vs. By which Embaſſage the States were excuſed from treating of the peace, without breach of their dutie and honour.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*">Shall we credit, whatſoeuer it pleaſes you to forge: Fie, what a deale of froth haue we heere?</note>Moreouer, what difficulties happened <hi>anno</hi> 1588. and 1589. about com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the ſeditions in <hi>Medenblick, Gertruydenbergh. Heuſden</hi> and other cities, and forts: What Prince <note n="a">What thinke you of this, moſt excellent Prince? You are acquainted with the fellowes wiles and deceits: know yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that couered fire breakes out vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently.</note> 
               <hi>Maurice</hi> writ to the Parliament, and Councell of England, to demonſtrate, that the aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Coronell <hi>Snoy</hi> impiouſly pretended the colour of Religion, in his plots and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries: What charges we were at againſt the Spaniſh Nauie, againſt the counſels and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> againſt the citie of <hi>Birghen apſome</hi> and the fortreſſes thereof, together with the territorie of <hi>Vander-Tholen.</hi> How the Prouince, and Citie of <hi>Vtricke</hi> had libertie giuen to depoſe illegitimate Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, and reſtore legitimate. How the agreements of peace betwixt <hi>Spaine</hi> &amp; <hi>England</hi> were <note n="(b)">Neuer was any man ſo ſhameleſſely confident in his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as is our <hi>Barneuelt.</hi>
               </note> intercepted by me: How an expedition was vndertaken againſt the Towne of <hi>Breda.</hi> By what meanes the gouernement of <hi>Gelderland, Vtricke,</hi> and <hi>Tranſyſulania</hi> was conferred vpon Prince <note n="(c)">Excellent Prince doe you thinke any of theſe Greekes to be without fraude?</note> 
               <hi>Maurice,</hi> was furthered and effected by me. What an expedition was made againſt the Cities of <hi>Nymeghen</hi> and <hi>Graues:</hi> what a building of a fort there was without <hi>Nymeghen;</hi> after what manner the fortreſſe of <hi>Terheide,</hi> and <hi>Steinbergh</hi> was taken, by what meanes all things were prepared, directed, and ſucceſſefully effected vntill the expedition of the yeere 91. when wee wonne <hi>Zutphen Deuenter,</hi> and <hi>Delfs-Ile,</hi> and other adiacent forts, and lands, when wee fortunately wonne <hi>Hulſt</hi> and <hi>Nymeghen</hi> in the ſame yeere: and how the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> to his great loſſe, and damage, was enforced to leaue the fort beyond <hi>Nimeghen</hi> it were too tedious to relate. I will onely ſay thus much: <note n="(d)">
                  <p>How eaſily would your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie ſuffer you to heare that of the Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t applyed to your ſelfe;
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Vnus homo nobis cunctando reſtituit rem.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>One onely man by graue and wiſe delay,</l>
                        <l>Preſeru'd the country made to th' fo a prey.</l>
                     </q>
But your ambition is apparant: and your vaunts proue you to be as vaine as Vanity it ſelfe.</p>
               </note> I had a principall hand in al theſe matters; as alſo in this that alwaies premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (Gods aſſiſtance) your Honours and Highneſſes lawfull authoritie was on a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine in more fauour, credite, and reſpect, then it hath euer beene heretofore.</p>
            <p>Now after all affaires of the States, all matters concerning Warre, Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Iuſtice, leuying of moneyes
<pb facs="tcp:21782:11"/>
was brought into ſome tolerable forme and order; I ſhewed your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Highneſſes <hi>Anno</hi> 1592. as well face to face, as by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in my abſence, that I had formerly complained more then once o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the weightineſſe of the Office impoſed vpon me, &amp; that I deſired to be freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the burthen therof. But our affairs being then perplexed, I fel ſhort of my wiſh. Then afterward all things being happily finiſhed and diſpatched, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued my ſuite to be diſcharged of the place, without expectation of any further <note n="(a)">
                  <p>Quis veteres auias tibi de pulmone reuellet?</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Who dares attempt to quite your bragging breſt,</l>
                     <l>Of this proud diuel, wherwith you are poſſeſt?</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Your bragges are vnreaſonable: and you then vent them, when you haue leaſt cauſe.</p>
               </note> recompence but this, to wit an immunitie euer after from the vndertaking of any other office and charge vvhatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</p>
            <p>But my Petition, though earneſt and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, preuailed not: and I was with my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour requeſted, and my pay <note n="(b)">
                  <p>A man may ſee you haue reade the Comedian, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued this out of him;
<q>
                        <l>All men are bound their ſelfe-good to procure,</l>
                        <l>And thereof in th' firſt place themſelues aſſure.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </note> purpoſely encreaſed, that I ſhould not giue ouer my Office, and it was declared this was heartily deſired of each member, and Citie of the whole aſſembly. Thus I was compelled to perſeuer in my charge and Office.</p>
            <p>From this time, <hi>viz:</hi> from the yeere ninty two, vntill the yeere 1608. I neuer left, nor was any way wanting to my Office. From the yeere <note n="(d)">
                  <hi>Now this baſe, impudent, and vaine-glorious fellow, this periur'd and adulterous naughty-packe enters afreſh into his bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariſme.</hi> Mais pourquoy t' en croyra on, puis qu' en vn champ tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n' ouys iamais la trompette? But who will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue him, who durſt neuer venture himſelfe within the hearing of the ſound of a trumpet? and euer after he continues in his vanity, and tragicall loftie ſtile?</note> 88. vnto the yeere 1606. full out, I went thirtie ſixe ſeuerall times to Prince-<hi>Maurice</hi> in his Campe, either ſent for by him, or otherwiſe deputed, that I might vnfould vnto him the courſe and order of our proceedings, and procure the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your decrees; which I performed to my commendation and praiſe, oftentimes <note n="(e)">Haue patience a while and wee will inroll you in the number of the Gods: but it muſt be the infernall ones.</note> beyond the hope and expectation of all men. In this <hi>interim</hi> too I vndertooke, and worthily performed foure <note n="(a)">Wonder, reader, and giue this mighty man the way. For he was ſent Embaſſadour from hence in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of a potent Common-weale. But why did you accept of thoſe Embaſſages (as you call them) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the entrance to your office you prouided, that you might be ſent no where out of the Prouince; but I know added ſome prouiſo &amp; exception: and I know moreouer, that your ambition gapes for great imploiment, &amp; an impotent, and vnreſtrained deſire of praiſe makes you aduenture your ſelfe blindfolded in purſuit thereof.</note> Princely &amp; roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Embaſſages, to the great good and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite
<pb facs="tcp:21782:12"/>
of the Countrey. And when a treatie tending to Peace was laboured in the Emperours name, and the Prince of <hi>Parmaes,</hi> in the names of <hi>Erueſte,</hi> and <hi>Albert</hi> Arch-Dukes, and the generall States of the aduerſe and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie faction; the <note n="(b)">You are an enemy to Peace, and ſhall neuer enioy peace. But I maruell you durſt be ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as to profeſſe ſo much. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince the intereſt payed for your debts (which were occaſioned by breach of the Peace) ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your impoſts, contributions, and exactions. Your ſelfe alone were the originall of theſe incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences. But what became of all theſe monies? Giue vp your accounts, for you muſt bee no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Steward.</note> breaking of this Peace coſt me a great deale of paines. Now ſince the King of <hi>France</hi> made a league with the King of <hi>England,</hi> the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Arch-Dukes, the money paid for our debts and other arrereages were ſo exceſſiue, that they amounted to more then the Subſidie &amp; contributions (though they were greatly raiſed) could ſatisfy, by the ſumme of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſix millions of Florens. Furthermore, the two laſt yeeres were paſſed ouer with much infamie and loſſe, and yet againe greater da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger was feared (two expeditions prepared by the enemy being hardly remoued out of the way) becauſe at the very inſtant time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine aides were both leſſe firme, and more burdenſome to the countrey, then hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were wont to be: and becauſe the intereſt-money came to that height, that the State of the whole ſeemed deſperate, as our Counſellours and Treaſurers three yeeres ſince had forewarned. And now after this aduertiſement, the burdens impoſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the reuenewes of the Countrey, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſixe or ſeuen millions of Florences, within the compaſſe of the ſaid three yeeres. <note n="(c)">Why doe you extoll this, as though it had beene effected by your induſtrie? You are not Iwis, the preſeruer, but the betrayer of your Countrey, and ſcatter-good thereof. You haue not relieued her, but thrust her into further debt: and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, which you would engroſſe, is either no commendation; or if it be any, it belongs not to you. And truely whereas the Spaniard made a compoſition on ſuch eaſie tearmes, in ſo deſperate a time, that muſt be aſcribed to the hidden counſell of God, who turnes all things to their good, whom he hath predeſtinated thereto. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, I was my ſelfe an eye witneſſe of ſuch abaſhment, in the ſubiects of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federated Prouinces, and an eare witneſſe of ſuch deſperate coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, as were neuer heretofore heard of: and therefore you coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned money (wherein there was a myſterie) with <hi>Peters</hi> floa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhip, and this inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>O yee of little faith, why doe you feare?</hi> Which you diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded amongſt the Orders, and heads of the State, as a preſent for honours ſake, not of dutie, according to a receiued cuſtome among you. Whereof I had a part, and doe profeſſe my ſelfe to be a well-willer of the good of the Common-weale, not of your facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But if God had not helped in theſe extremities, thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels had beene to litttle purpoſe, and certaine others more to bee abhorred (I ſpeake the truth) which proceeded from deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Here no man ought to maruell, that is
<pb facs="tcp:21782:12"/>
not deſtitute of reaſon, why (ſince it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared that the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Arch-Dukes yeelded for their part vnto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces their rights and libertie, and this granted, would end all matters with the Lords of the States, not now as their vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, and ſubiects, but Gouernours of free-dominions, to which they made no claime: and ſince it was hoped that by this meanes ſo long, bloudy, and chargeable a warre, might ſort to an honourable wiſhed and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure end) why, I ſay, ſuch a meeting was intended. At my firſt entrance into this mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (wherein the Common Councell, and Embaſſadours of <hi>France, Great-Britain, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> and of the Electors <hi>Palatine,</hi> and <hi>Brandeburge,</hi> and diuers Princes <hi>Euang:</hi> of <hi>Germanie</hi>) I plainely perceiued the firſt attempts of my aduerſaries againſt my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and proceedings, both in open aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and in libels, which were caſt out: which was done by their directions, who were <note n="(a)">This is but your opinion and coniecture, but others know there is no ſuch matter.</note> offended at this treatie concerning Peace. I declared ſo much to your Honours and Highneſſes: and proffered neuertheleſſe to reſigne my offices, and liue a priuate life: and therefore of ſet purpoſe I abſented my ſelfe from the Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>But <note n="(b)">This was kindely done of them, howſoeuer the feare of a greater inconuenience made them chooſe this: &amp; you laught in your ſleeue, when you perceiued that the Foxes skinne auailed there, where the Lyons could not. You are very politick, I wiſh you to continue ſo.</note> I vnderſtood both by vvord of mouth, by the commiſſaries of the Nobles and free-cities, and alſo by letters, that the Aſſembly of your Honours and Highneſſes did with one accord approue of my offices, and ſeruices, and willed me to perſiſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and againe reſort vnto the Aſſembly, &amp; that they would furthermore eſteeme ſo of all inconueniences, which happened vnto me, as if they ſhould happen to the generall Aſſemblie. I obeyed your Honours, and
<pb facs="tcp:21782:13"/>
Highneſſes heerein, perſeuered in my office, brought the treatie to a deſired and <note n="(a)">
                  <p>
                     <hi>You know what</hi> Menelaus <hi>ſayes in</hi> Homer: <q>—<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</q> It is worth the wiſhing for, to bee without the compaſſe of exception.</p>
               </note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable iſſue, and with others ſubcribed thereto. <note n="(b)">
                  <p>Better &amp; better ſtil, but you hunt after prayſe with too great earneſtneſſe: Was not the once vttering of theſe things ſufficient? But happely doating old age hath depriued you of your memorie, ſo that you obſerue not, that in a ſhort ſpace you repeate the ſame thing ouer and ouer: But the Reader muſt hold him excuſed, hee was ſometime wiſe, new hee dotes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nam quaecun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſedens modo legerat, haec eadem ſtans</l>
                     <l>Profert, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> eadem cantabit verſibus ijſdem.</l>
                     <l>What ſitting earſt he read, that ſtanding hee rehearſes;</l>
                     <l>And vents the ſelf ſame things all in the ſelfe ſame verſes.</l>
                     <l>—<hi>Gaudent</hi>—</l>
                  </q>
               </note> I was imploied alſo in diuerſe Treaties, vvith the Embaſſadours of the Queene Mother in <hi>France,</hi> with Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours in <hi>England,</hi> both as long as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid meeting held, and before: as alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the ſame. Moreouer, I was made go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the forces, which were ſent by the King of <hi>France,</hi> and put in truſt to make euen the debts betwixt vs and the King of <hi>England:</hi> all the agreements whereof vvere ſealed by me.</p>
            <p>Afterward I was chiefe inſtrument, and procurer of vniting the Prouinces, which the King of <hi>England</hi> helped firſt of all more then 24 yeares one after another: afterward with the countenance and authoritie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and great ſtore of money, and now (by the care and direction of the Kings of the foreſaid Kingdome) things were brought to that paſſe, which I tolde you a little before, that they could fully diſcharge the debtes, wherein they were engaged, and redeeme their cities, and places laid to pledge, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer their bonds and obligations.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(c)">
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Garrula ſecuri narrare pericula nautae.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So Mariners when all is ſafe and wel,</l>
                     <l>Their perills ouerblowne doe ioy to tell.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Yet you ſooth your ſelfe too much, and make your ſelfe the <hi>Atlas,</hi> and ſuſtainer of the whole ſtate of <hi>Holland:</hi> But let mee tell you in your eare, for I hope you will vnderſtand mee; <hi>Si ſuelen algunos hombres ſubir tan alto, que ſe pierden à ſe miſmos de viſta. Many haue mounted ſo high, that haue loſt the benefit of their ſight.</hi> It is the language of a nation, with whom you are now familiar, and well acquainted.</p>
               </note> And I ſettled the money-matters of the Prouinces in thoſe tearms, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of the Admiralties, which before in the yeare 1609 were burdened with about two Millions, and eight hundreth thouſand Florens, were ſo eaſed, that whereas in the beginning of my office we paid yearely pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of 12 in the 100, and 2 for brokeage, now inſtead thereof, our laſt borrowed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is at 16, and three in the hundreth for brokeage, to bee redeemed at 9 in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, or at vſe at ſixteene.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21782:13"/>Whereas <note n="(a)">Some <hi>Times</hi> haue their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie, and ſome <hi>Oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> their time: and there will both time and oportunitie bee found, to put vp complaints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you: doe you conceiue mee?</note> then after ſo many, ſo great, ſo ſingular and extraordinarie offices, and ſeruices for ſo long a time continually performed, the adminiſtration of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth is now complained of: whereas it is pretended, that they know not whence and what I am: whereas I am accounted a forreiner, a ſtranger, and that other ſuch-like vnſeemely reports are noiſed abroad: theſe things muſt needs trouble mee, hauing ſuſtained more then 32 yeares the office of the diſpoſer of the affaires of the country, in all your Honours and Highneſſes Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and being poſſeſſed in the ſaid Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of another place and office nine yeares before. But I anſwer; I was borne at the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <note n="(b)">Is it ſo? come you from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mersfort?</hi> then you know how to bragge and ſwagger, triumph, and ioy in it: But how doe you proue your ſelfe to be of that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Familie, or to bee legitimate? If <hi>New-kerke</hi> in the <hi>Welue</hi> wil giue you a Teſtimonie of your legitimateneſſe, I will eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it: they may iuſtly make claime of a place in the meetings of <hi>Gelderland,</hi> you vniuſtly. But I ſpare to ſpeake of theſe things, and you happely were borne in a place of no note, where you were not known to your neareſt friends.</note> 
               <hi>Amersfort,</hi> where my predeceſſor in office was alſo borne. By my fathers ſide, I deriue my pedigree from the ancient and noble ſtocke of the <hi>Olden-barneuells,</hi> the line deſcending euery way lawfully from our anceſtors for many yeares: w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
               <hi>Olden-bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuells</hi> for ſome hundred yeares appeared al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie vpon warning in the Prouincial aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and other meetings, of the Gentrie of <hi>Welue,</hi> as they doe yet euen at this day. By my mothers ſide, a matrone of worthy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, I deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lawfully euery way too from the worſhipful family of<note n="(d)">I know nothing but good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that <hi>Family:</hi> yet I adde thus much, but not in ſcorne, <hi>Such once we were,</hi> &amp;c. And I further maruaile, why you ſhould ſo carefully ſearch, and as it were mendicate theſe things, for you haue no reaſon at all to make mention of the familie of <hi>Lockehorſt</hi> (which you doe a little after). I know both that Familie and you, and therein Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants alſo, at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in the <hi>Warmeſtraet:</hi> but you reply, hee is an <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt.</hi> So by the ſame reaſon <hi>Wynbergen</hi> of <hi>Amersfort</hi> ſhall bee no Gentleman, becauſe hee goes in black. It is not the Garment, but the Place and Office which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſes men. <hi>Winbergen</hi> is principall of the <hi>Perfectiſts,</hi> and you of the <hi>Arminians,</hi> both your Religions are ſtarke naught.</note> 
               <hi>Amersfort,</hi> which in progreſſe of time, after the branching out
<pb facs="tcp:21782:14"/>
(hereof, was called <hi>Wede:</hi> and this was alſo of good account, and ancient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo, vvhich now ſome 300, or 400 yeares ſince, (in treaties of peace bewixt the Count of <hi>Holland,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Vtricke,</hi> and others, as alſo in affaires with the gouernours of <hi>Amſtel,</hi> and <hi>Woerden</hi>) was ranked in the order of gentlemen, and was poſſeſſed with ſome thouſands of acres of land, goodly Lordſhips, great ſtore of goods, and iuriſdictions.</p>
            <p>Neither can I be accounted for a ſtranger in <hi>Holland,</hi> ſince that is contrary to the vnion made, heretofore more then 80 yeares, in the raigne of the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Charles,</hi> of happy memory, betwixt the <hi>Hollander,</hi> and the men of <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricke,</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland</hi> being earneſt ſuiters therefore. Since which time both the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricke,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricke</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> haue beene admitted promiſcuouſly into all offices of both places, and are ſo yet. My accuſer will take order to haue my life and acts written: but I <note n="(a)">Your paines wil bee fruitleſſe; for there will bee nothing in the diſcourſe worth the hearing: but this your accuſer whoſoeuer he is, if hee doe vndertake the ſetting forth of your Acts, and life, I hope hee will painte you in your proper colours, and this feare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready torments you.</note> will ſaue him the labour, and doe it my ſelfe briefly and ſhortly.</p>
            <p>When I <note n="(b)">Who were your Schoole-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters? for it is of great import vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what teachers, and diſcipline, youth is brought vp.</note> had made ſome progreſſe, how meane ſoeuer in my ſtudies, I went in the yeare 1564 to the <note n="(c)">Accurſed was the <hi>Haighe</hi> to haue <hi>Berneuell</hi> for an inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. Certainely you deſerue to be vſed as the <hi>Bore</hi> is, which is yeerely ſent from <hi>Vtricke</hi> to the <hi>Haighe,</hi> neither ſhall the reformed Church euer bee at peace, till this be done. You know wheter I will bring you.</note> Haigh; and there, that &amp; the yeare following I practiſed. The yeares 66 and 67, I followed my ſtudie at <hi>Louane</hi> and <hi>Rohines</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> Many other ſtudents, and my ſelfe were conſtrained to leaue <hi>France</hi> about the later time of the yeare 1567, by reaſon of ciuil warre then ariſing: from thence therefore trauailing thorough <hi>Burgundie,</hi> the Arch-dukedome, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Biſantiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Mompeillart,</hi> I came tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough <hi>Switzerland</hi> to <hi>Buſille,</hi> and from -thence along the riuer <hi>Rhene</hi> to <hi>Colen.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prouided at <hi>Colen</hi> with a freſh ſupplie for my iourney, I went to <note n="(a)">This was one of the chiefe reaſons why I writte this Apologie (moſt learned <hi>Pareues</hi> and kinde brother) vnto you. Hee auerres hee ſucked in this poyſon at <hi>Heydelberge,</hi> that hee was made an <hi>Arminian</hi> at <hi>Heydel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge,</hi> before <hi>Arminius</hi> his name was heard of: That hee may diſgrace your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, traduce your Doctors of Diuinity, &amp; fraudulently ſcandalize the antient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion. Though the impoſtor fawne, yet he bites, priuily faſtning in his poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned teeth: but he ſhall not carry it away ſcot-free. Wherefore I leaue him to you (famous <hi>Pareus</hi>) and your iudicious and learned penne: canuaſe him according to his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: ſo may you thriue, as you perſiſt to whippe him againe and againe, and ceaſe not from the dawning of the day, vntill the ſhutting vp thereof.</note> 
               <hi>Heidelbergs;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21782:14"/>
where I followed the ſtudie of the lawe: and diuinity diſputations being then frequently held concerning <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> I for my part imbraced this doctrine, as ſound, and <hi>(b)</hi> Chriſtian;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That a good Chriſtian ought to beleeue, that he is predeſtinated vnto ſaluation by the grace of God, and for the ſatisfaction which his Sauiour and Redeemer made for his ſinnes: and that by the ſame grace of God hee hath receiued this faith, whereby he firmely beleeues,</hi>
               <note n="(c)">How ſound and Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like your Religion is, euery Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler knows, and further that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and wicked impieties were hatched there, or in confederated <hi>Belgia</hi> by this your Religion.</note> 
               <hi>that his ſaluation is onely founded in the grace of God, and merites of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt: and that though hee ſlip into grieuous ſinnes, neuertheleſſe he ought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to hope and beleeue, that God will not ſuffer him to continue therein, but that hee ſhall in mercy be conuerted, and brought to repentance, that intreats for mercie; and laſtly, that hee ſhall perſeuere in the faith vnto his liues end.</hi> With which opinion that very yeare I acquainted the two diuinitie profeſſors, <hi>Bocquin,</hi> and <hi>Zanchius,</hi> and <hi>Oleuian</hi> alſo their principall prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, who ſaid, that <hi>I might reſt therein without any further enquirie.</hi> I haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in this minde through Gods grace now 50 yeares: and being wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie 71 yeares olde at this preſent, I hope I ſhall from henceforth liue and die therein. Concerning a further ſearch of my religion, this was my ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict and profeſſion, (which my great-grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father <hi>Nicholas</hi> 
               <note n="(a)">While you ſtriue to approue your Religion, you ſtick not to make your great-Grandfather irreligious: But a word or two in your eare. <hi>You are an Atheiſt,</hi> you neyther beleeue in <hi>God</hi> nor care for him. And ſo much your verdict and ſaying in the poynt of Faith, vnfalli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly proues.</note> 
               <hi>Olden-Berneuell</hi> (vvhoſe wife <hi>Adelheidis</hi> of <hi>Lockehorſt,</hi> my great-grandmother deſcended legitimately and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly from the ancient houſe of <hi>Lockehorſt,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is ſituate nie <hi>Amersford</hi>) left behind him) <hi>It is the ſureſt faith to know nothing.</hi> I trauailed through <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> in the yeares 68, and 69: and hauing finiſhed my courſe of ſtudie, at my parents charges I came vnto the <note n="(b)">Let the <hi>Haigh</hi> dreſſe this beaſt as hee deſerues: or if ſhee bee pleaſed firſt to fatte him with the maſt of her Wood, let her doe it quickly, leſt hee ſlippe away out of her, for the Towne hath no ward nor gates to preuent his flight.</note> 
               <hi>Haigh,</hi> to dwell there, and was <hi>Aduocate</hi> of the Court. <note n="(c)">See how the Foxe holds with the Hare, and runnes with the Houndes.</note> I was one of the three <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocates,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21782:15"/>
who in the yeare 1572 firſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged his Excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of famous memory to be the lawfull gouernour of <hi>Holland:</hi> and the ſame yeare I determined with my ſelfe to ſpend <note n="(d)">
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſe velut ſtricto quoties Lucilius ardens</l>
                        <l>Infremuit, tubet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uditor cui frigida mens eſt</l>
                        <l>Crimimbus, tanta ſudant praecordia culpa.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>When vexed Poets take their pens in hand,</l>
                        <l>Meaning therwith the faulty times to bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</l>
                        <l>Guilt dies the fearful bluſhing Readers face:</l>
                        <l>Their troubled thoughts conſtraine them ſweat apace.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>But you are ſo earneſt in diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all ſuſpicion from you, that wee cannot eaſilie beleeue you.</p>
               </note> all my thoughts, and vtmoſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ability herein, viz. that there might be an irreco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cilable alienation betwixt me &amp; the Spaniard, and his adherents: which I alſo effected, both in cauſes <note n="(e)">What haue you to doe with Church-matters? doe you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preferre ciuill authority be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Churches, becauſe you would bee Pope? I know both this and you, and that you are an eaues-dropper.</note> Eccleſiaſticall &amp; Ciuill, and all others whatſoeuer. In the beginning of the yeare 1573, fearing leſt the Spaniard would <note n="(f)">I wiſh hee had, for this might haue preuented many enſuing euils.</note> ſurprize mee at the <hi>Haigh,</hi> I remoued to <hi>Delfe.</hi> That yeare I was imploied in honeſt imploiments: your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Highneſſes vſed mee as <hi>Aduocate</hi> of the Court of <hi>Holland,</hi> as did alſo moſt of the Lords and Nobles, and not a few of the free-Cities, Colledges, and Officialls. The ſame yeare I went to war at my owne char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, amongſt the number of the voluntarie ſouldiers, to raiſe the ſiege at <note n="(a)">How great puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t had you eſcaped (to which you are now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued) if you had eyther bin ſhot, or hanged at <hi>Harlem-ſiege,</hi> or kept the Gates at <hi>Leyden</hi> with <hi>Peter Pau,</hi> or beene otherwiſe humbled there, vpon the blew ſtone in the great Broad-ſtreete; or beene drowned at <hi>Soetnier</hi> in the Riuer adioyning thereto?</note> 
               <hi>Harlem,</hi> from whence <note n="(b)">
                  <hi>Vn beau mourir c'eſt mourir dans ſes Armes.</hi> Yet the Prouerb ſayes, It is a fayre death to die in Armes.</note> I freed my ſelfe very faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. In the yeare 74. I was perſonally in many expeditions, to breake vp the ſiege at <hi>Leiden:</hi> but while we lay before <hi>Soetnier</hi> I fell ſicke, and was hindered from raiſing the ſiege. In the yeare 75. I married a <note n="(a)">Of what houſe was ſhee, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or ignoble? deſcended of a Marchant, or a Countrie man? I maruell why you conceale this, who were ſo farre ouerſeen by reaſon of vaine-glory, that you pulled, by the head and ſhoulders, the Familie of <hi>Lockhorſt</hi> into your linage, and confounded it therewith: you ſhould haue gratified your ſonnes thus farre, that hereafter in publike writings and teſtimonies they might haue ſhewed their nobilitie, and haue endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to thruſt themſelues among the aſſemblies of <hi>Gelderland.</hi> This would not haue ſtood both with yours, and their honours. But ſhee is ſome baſe woman, and of the meaner ſort: and (that he may not gull the Reader) ſhall I ſay any more? ſhe is a Papiſt, yea and perhaps worſe. Euery man thinkes his owne Crow white, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if it tend to profit.</note> wife: vvhom I
<pb facs="tcp:21782:15"/>
loued for her perſon, but the more for that ſhe brought with her in preſent for her dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and the aſſured hope of increaſing and mending thereof. In the year 76. I was woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to accept a <hi>Counſellers</hi> and <hi>Penſioners</hi> place in the city of <note n="(b)">If you had beene tied to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus</hi> his ſtatue, and both it and you flung headlong from the bridge, none now at <hi>Roterdam</hi> had beene infected with <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> his frenſie, and oppoſed their lawfull Magiſtrates.</note> 
               <hi>Roterdam.</hi> I had good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which induced mee to vndertake that office; and therein for the ſpace of 9 yeares I performed <note n="(c)">I will relate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: and now take this for one with you; viz. you accepted this place for feare otherwiſe to haue gone many times ſupperleſſe to bed.</note> extraordinary ſeruices both to the ſaid City, and the whole countrie in generall: in reſpect whereof the Conſulls, and Gouernours of <hi>Roterdam</hi> did not onely honourably thanke mee, but conferred the office of <hi>Aduocate-Generall</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> vpon me in the yeare 1586, my <note n="(f)">I remember the Man, you meane him with the golden Armour.</note> brother being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected into my place, (that this might teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their gracious acceptance of my ſeruice) who continued alſo in their ſeruice to his dying day. What I perſonally performed in this office beſtowed by your Honours, what
<note n="(d)">To your bed, and your belly.</note>
               <note n="(e)">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Le paon loue auſsi tot fait la rue,</l>
                     <l>Et le recache alors, alors qu'on ne le loue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Peacock when he's viewd disſheuels his faire traine:</l>
                     <l>When Men draw back their eyes, he knits it vp againe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </note>
others vnder me, I haue <note n="(a)">Yes, we knew long agoe.</note> briefly heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſed. I can <note n="(b)">Looke, the man ſweares: que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe he deſires to be a good man, without doubt to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo: But he is ſtarke naught, yea guiltie of periurie, for ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thus: for he cares not a ſtraw, eyther for this or that ſide ſo himſelfe may be ſure to be prouided for.</note> truely auouch thus much for my ſelfe, that I from the yeare 72, to this preſent, haue alwaies beene as <note n="(c)">Impudent, thou art as changeable as the weather, and dareſt thou ſpeake thus?</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably forward to defend the countries right, both with my goods, bloud, <note n="(d)">None will take your word, Paraſite, and you haue no proofe: where are the Wounds, where are the Skarres, where are the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages receiued in the common wealths behalfe? While you brag that you ſerued as a voluntarie ſouldier, you ranne away from <hi>Harlem</hi> in the expedition to <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> you counterfeited your ſelf to be ſicke, you neuer were in any battell: nay when you were a yong man, you neuer durſt looke a Souldier in the face; what will you doe when you are old? <hi>Le fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, &amp; la perditata dei mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri ſono le collare &amp; le me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daglie Dei famigliari Morti:</hi> Wounds and loſt limbes, are the golden chaynes, and brooches of Mars his followers. You haue womaniſh and dainty lims, fitter for ſporting and the Chamber, then the Campe: And certainely if you had but a ſparkle of a Souldiers courage in you, you would not ſo carefully haue reckoned vp your ſafe iourneyes to <hi>Graue-Maurice</hi> his Campe.</note> and
<pb facs="tcp:21782:16"/>
life euen to the vtmoſt, againſt the vſurped claim of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federats, as <note n="(e)">Theſe are the leaſings of a Coward, for there are multitudes, which out ſtrippe you herein. Euen I for my part dare challenge you, and haue both gone through greater matters, and am more ready to part with my life for the good of the Countrey, then you or any of your ſect. I forbeare to ſay more at this time, leaſt if I draw the curtaine quite open, all ſhould be diſcouered.</note> any one whatſoeuer, (I except none) &amp; will continue ſo for the time to come by Gods <note n="(f)">Which lies in your bootes, after the kitchin-wench hath greaſed them.</note> grace. In like <note n="(g)">You are nothing but words.</note> manner that I haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the vtmoſt maintained with all ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie, ſinceritie, and reſolution, the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, liberties, rights, and iuriſdictions of the Prouinces, of the particular members &amp; cities of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland;</hi> and doe preſume, that I ſhall <note n="(h)">You are too troubleſome with your repetitions: You were ill taught in your minoritie at <hi>Louaine:</hi> my opinion is, that eyther the Monkes learned you to chant it in their quier, or old beldames to vſe the Diſtaffe.</note> perſiſt in this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe by Gods leaue to the end, without alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or change. I haue alwaies as much, if not more then any reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred &amp; extolled the deſerts of my Lo. &amp; Maſter, the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge,</hi> in procuring the liberty, &amp; rights of the Prouinces, and the maintenance of the true Euangelicall religion. I doubt not, but theſe honourable perſonages following will giue mee teſtimony <note n="(a)">But why doe you not bring in theſe teſtimonies? eſpecially the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of <hi>Graue-Maurice,</hi> and <hi>Prince Henry,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe which ſuruiue? Doe you take your ſelfe to bee a man of ſo great credit, that your word will ſerue the turne? I warrant you none beleeues you: not thoſe Princes whom you reckon vp: yea you ſeeke to bleare their eyes &amp; put tricks vpon them: but your plottes ſpeede not, <hi>God is on their ſide.</hi>
               </note> thereof. The Lady and Dutcheſſe-dowager his Excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cies, of happy remembrance, his widow, my good Lords.
<pb facs="tcp:21782:16"/>
The now Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> and Prince <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> his ſonnes: the Counteſſe <hi>ab Hohenlo,</hi> 
               <note n="(b)">I, Yes, ſhee owes the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts a good turne, eſpecially ſince the tokens of Prince <hi>William</hi> his death are yet to bee ſeene in the Monaſtery where ſhe liues. But if I be not much deceiued in her, ſhe is a profeſſor of the ancient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, and an enemie to you, and your followers.</note> the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Portingall,</hi> the Electoreſſe, and Counteſſe <note n="(c)">What affection thoſe Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſes of Germany beare you and your <hi>Arminians,</hi> I know better then your ſelfe. Yea, I know that you moſt freely cite them for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, who are further off: as though heere were not ſome preſent, who reſpected the welfare of low-Germany, and knew not your fetches and treacheries long agoe. You deale cunningly <hi>(Arminian)</hi> you doe: and that you may ſupplant the true Goſpellers, you pretend your ſelfe to bee a Goſpeller, and one of the reformed antient religion. In the meane time, what our Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſes thinke of your report, what a reward your preſumptuous impudencie deſerues, if no bodie make you ſhortly feele indeed, I will tell you by writing, vnleſſe you repent betimes.</note> 
               <hi>Palatine,</hi> widowe. The Dutcheſſe of <hi>Bouillon, Toars.</hi> The Counteſs of <hi>Hunno:</hi> and Counteſſe <hi>Palatine Bipout:</hi> daughters to the Princes wife, and all their commiſſaries ioyntly. And I haue yet in my cuſtodie many letters of thankefulneſſe, and writings of remembrances.</p>
            <p>How <note n="(e)">
                  <p>The vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a benefite is an vpbraiding thereof: but ſtill to harpe vpon this ſtring (as you ſhamefully doe) is a monſtrous reproach. Then thoſe viſitations, if neceſſary, were they not enioined you either by your place and office, or by the command of the honourable, and mighty Lords of the States? Why doe you prate then, if you being a ſeruant exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted your maſters behests? Why doe you bragge of your mercenarie labour? But what ſay you to this (moſt famous and gentle Prince of Orenge?) I ſee he leuels at you with his weapons point, and menaces cloſe wounds, yet moſt noxious and pernicious to the author thereof. And heere thoſe your diuine words wonderfully affect &amp; pleaſe me, as alſo all the approuers of the ancient Reformation, which I muſt needes expreſſe in a more loftie language.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>— Ben che trafitto</l>
                     <l>Io piango il feritor, non le ferite</l>
                     <l>Che l'error ſuo piu ch' el mio mal mi peſa.</l>
                     <l>That ſuch a hand could wound, it grieues me more,</l>
                     <l>Then th' anguiſh, which I ſuffer by my ſore.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Yet, howſoeuer the ſpeech chalengeth commendation, take heed, leſt you too confidently continue your enemies aſſaults: eſpecially, ſince no treaſon is ſo cloſe and dangerous, as that which is cloked with the name of duty and friendſhip.</p>
               </note> much I haue laboured in furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the gouernement, and performance of of your renowned <hi>Princes Mandates:</hi> how I haue beene with him in his Campe thirty <note n="(d)">If you had, we ſhould haue ſeene them long before this time.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:21782:17"/>
ſix ſeuerall times, ſomtimes a whole moneth together, ſometimes leſſe. How many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times I haue gone vp, and came down his chamber ſtaires, that knowledge of your mutuall affaires, and vnity of your mindes and conſents might be continued betwixt you, his honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Excellencie beſt knowes. His Excellencies honour and authoritie were alwaies deere vnto me, and my endeauours were wholly bent to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his deſires, ſo farre forth as was lawfull for me. And I verely perſwade my ſelfe, that his Excellencie had and exerciſed more ample authoritie in <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> then in any other part of his Prouinces and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement. I aſſiſted his Excellencie in all his wiſhes, neither was I euer wanting to my power to himſelfe, or thoſe whom it pleaſed him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto mee, as farre as my honour and oath would warrant mee. Thus <note n="(a)">
                  <p>If they had knowne your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, they would not haue bought your affinitie. For you are one of them the Poet ſpeakes of, <hi>Faciem cum aſpicias eorum, haud mali videntur, opera &amp; fide fallunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Their faces promiſe truth and honeſtie.</l>
                     <l>Their deeds are full of guile and treacherie.</l>
                  </q>
               </note> his Excellencie alwaies thought: thus he ſpake of me; and gaue euidence thereof many waies, both in reſpect of my ſelfe and my children, prouiding for both my ſonnes, out of thoſe eſtates which were in his gift and diſpoſing. Which I deſired his Excellencie to do, to the intent that they might bee tied vnto him in more ſtrait bonds, and obliged to his faithfull ſeruice. I married all my children into thoſe <note n="(a)">
                  <p>If they had knowne your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, they would not haue bought your affinitie. For you are one of them the Poet ſpeakes of, <hi>Faciem cum aſpicias eorum, haud mali videntur, opera &amp; fide fallunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Their faces promiſe truth and honeſtie.</l>
                     <l>Their deeds are full of guile and treacherie.</l>
                  </q>
               </note> families, who were alwaies reputed the greateſt well-willers of the Countrey; and both thoſe, Princes: I meane, the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Sonne.</hi> My eldeſt ſonne to the onely daughter, and heire of the Lord of <hi>Brant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> whoſe <note n="(b)">Heree againe you bring in a Catalogue of yours, and your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Progenitors. But what doth this concerne you? Was your Wife of the degree of a Gentlewoman? Was your Grandmother ſo too? your ſonne is not admitted into any of the Aſſemblies of the <hi>Welue.</hi> No, not though his wife be an heire.</note> Grandfather, a Prince of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memory reſpected, and vſed as the beſt deſeruing Gentleman in <hi>Zeland.</hi> My yonger ſonne to the <note n="(c)">Your enquirie findes out heires for your ſonnes, for no other reaſon, but becauſe they are rich, this was knowne long agoe. One thing I maruell at: Why, ſince you requeſted <hi>Philip Marnixius</hi> his daughter in marriage for your ſonne, you did not rather praiſe him for piety, and diligence in making bookes againſt the Papiſts and Monkes, amongst which his <hi>Bee-hiue,</hi> and tranſlation of the Pſalmes into Verſe are moſt excellent: but you only mind high matters; and whatſoeuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes religion, that you ſlightly paſſe ouer. You neither beleeue in God, nor feare him.</note> onely daughter and heire of the Lord of <hi>Saint Aldegonde,</hi> whoſe father and grand-father were great and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table States-men, and wiſhed all good to
<pb facs="tcp:21782:17"/>
his Excellencie. My <note n="(d)">If you were your ſonne in law his owne father, you might iuſtly triumph, and lawfully defend your cauſe. Now ſeeing you are more fearefull then a Hart, you trouble your ſelfe with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of other mens actions to no purpoſe.</note> eldeſt daughter, to a noble mans ſonne, <hi>viz. Lancelot of</hi> 
               <note n="(e)">Did not the true race of the houſe of <hi>Brederode</hi> faile, and ſurceaſe, vvhen the reſidue of that noble family (within the compaſſe of a few late yeeres) <hi>viz.</hi> foure male children, periſhed altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</note> 
               <hi>Brederode,</hi> while he liued <hi>Lord of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eenhuyſe,</hi> who tooke part with the Lords, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt vnion was made amongſt them for the libertie of that Countrey, and alſo againſt the Spaniſh Inquiſition; vvho was beſieged at <hi>Harlem,</hi> and there had his head cut off: my yonger daughter to the Lord Gouernour <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ander Myle</hi> his ſonne. Who alwaies ſhewed and approued himſelf to bee a faithfull, and good friend to the Countrey, to the <note n="(f)">Yea, of the ancient reformed religion: with which yours being compared is hereticall, and falſe; and your ſelfe the ſonne of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> true religion, and to both the Princes. I perſiſted conſtantly in a <note n="(g)">Here is a lie vvith a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Our ancient religion is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable with Gods word: yours contrarie thereto, and diueliſh: and your opinion concerning pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination was ſuggeſted by hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Furies. The griefe, whereof hee makes a ſhowe, is counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and if one doite might pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a rope to hang all the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the ancient reformed religion, &amp;c. Whatſoeuer his writing ſpeakes, I wiſh the reader to aduiſe of. For my part I will not ſet a marke vpon euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular lie in this place. Hereafter I ſhall haue fitter occaſion to doe it.</note> religion agreeable to Gods holy word, and ſincere doctrine, and in my fore-vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red opinion concerning predeſtination. I was heartily ſorie for the diſſenſions grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betwixt the <hi>Remonſtrancers,</hi> and <hi>Contra-remonſtrancers.</hi> I alwaies vſed my vtmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours, that they might not breake forth, and bee publiſhed abroad: and obtained firſt, that <hi>Arminius</hi> his cauſe might be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in priuate, ſundry Eccleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hauing the ouerſight and hearing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And for this purpoſe the matter was reaſoned in the Lord of <hi>Noortwicke</hi> of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memory, his houſe, as the more anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ouerſeer of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Leiden.</hi> Afterward it was commenced in a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation betwixt <hi>Gomar</hi> and <hi>Arminius,</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of diuers Churches of both parties being vmpires. I neither ſimply accepted, nor reiected either parties opinion, ſince I
<pb facs="tcp:21782:18"/>
               <note n="(a)">
                  <p>Yet let me tell you, that he neither thought ſo, neither was it poſſible he ſhould. And how can truth, and apparant falſehood bee ioined, or agree together? The one is inconstant, and variable, the other firme and ſtable.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>La Verité d'un Cube droit ſe forme,</l>
                     <l>Cube contraire au leger mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uement,</l>
                     <l>Son plan carré iamais ne ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,</l>
                     <l>Et en tous ſens a touſiours meme forme.</l>
                     <l>The truth reſembles, right, the right Cubes figure;</l>
                     <l>The Cube contrarie to light inſtabilitie,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe quadrant flatneſs neuer doth disfigure,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſolid forme admits no mutabilitie.</l>
                  </q>
               </note> vnderſtood by a ſecond writing, and learned inſtruction of the King of <hi>England,</hi> that both of them might be tolerated, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preiudice to the truth in Chriſtian vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; charitie. And I will beware <note n="(b)">For all your warineſſe wee will conuince you to be the ring-leader, and originall of them all.</note> of iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the authors of theſe Tragedies, and hurliburlies. But I <note n="(c)">What an age is this, vvhat faſhions are therein! you perceiue, reader, (for I cannot chooſe but interrupt you) that the Megari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans counterfaite teares deſerue more credit then his. Heauen ſtands ſtill, and the earth ſhakes in admiration of this impudence: He makes the Synod, the Diuines and Miniſters of your Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, the raiſers of the troubles in Holland, that he may baniſh them from thence. O monſtrous impiety!</note> ſuppoſe the greateſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill proceeded from a certaine decree of a Synode, which inioined the diuinity Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of <hi>Leiden</hi> and all the Preachers thereof, that in the feare of God they ſhould attend to thoſe things, which were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in the Confeſſion of <hi>Holland,</hi> and a Catechiſme of <hi>Heidelberge:</hi> and if they doubted of any thing, that they take note of it &amp; ſend it to their Claſſes. Which Decree was cauſed by all thoſe former Church-differences and controuerſies, which tooke their originall from <hi>Gaſper Coolchaes, H. Harbarts, Taco Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brandts, Cornelius Wiggers,</hi> and many more about the vnderſtanding, meaning, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent interpretation of certaine points con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the two forenamed writings, and chiefely about the point of <hi>Gods Predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And that therefore your Honours, and Highneſſes, in the yeere 1597. vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that the Confeſſion was to be reuiſed and corrected by a Synodall Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For after your Commiſſioners had certified you concerning the fore-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Decree of the Synode, you iudged that it vvas not conuenient that the doubts of the Profeſſors, and Preachers, ſhould bee deliuered to their ſeuerall <hi>Claſſes,</hi> fearing leaſt by this meanes an vnquenchable fire of diſſenſion might bee kindled amongſt the Diuines. Wherefore you determined that thoſe doubts ſhould be kept in priuate, either by your ſelues, or your Deputies, vntill a
<pb facs="tcp:21782:18"/>
Synode ſhould bee aſſembled, and that then they ſhould be diſcreetly laid open, and vnfoulded for the vſe and benefite of the Church, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>To <note n="(a)">
                  <hi>Let the Reader, whoſoeuer he is, tread warily, and circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heere.</hi> Eſtamos à tiempo, que merecer la coſa, es princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal parte para no alancarla. Wee liue in ſuch times, as to deſerue a good turne is the next way to loſe it.</note> ouerthrow this Synodall Decree, and your determination, certaine Acts were exhibited by ſome of the <hi>Almarick Claſſis,</hi> which were reade ouer in a Claſſicall mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (in which ſome Preachers, not of the meaner ſort, of that order then appeared) and it was knowne that all Preachers ought to haue ſubſcribed thereto. Fiue Preachers ſhewed themſelues very backward in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing, as though the matter had beene ſtrange and new. They vvere threatned with the Churches cenſure, then they complained vnto you: you appointed that ſuch like proceedings and cenſures ſhould be differred for a time; as contrarie to the foreſaid Decree of a Synode, and your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination. They which were of the <hi>Claſſis</hi> maintained they were not bound to obey your Decrees. You perſeuered in your determination. They which were of the Synode of <hi>North-Holland</hi> ioined themſelues to the <hi>Claſſis</hi> and made a great complaint of the prohibition before-mentioned. By theſe and ſuch like manners of proceeding by the ſect of the <hi>Remonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> the Preachers were <note n="(a)">Diſſimulation ſuites well heere, leſt haply you ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer your affection to your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whom you ſtirred vp to ſedition.</note> moued (fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leſt this might be their chance) to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite their Remonſtrance.</p>
            <p>I <note n="(b)">Which you ſuppreſſed leſt the ſtates ſhould be offended, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe your fellowes in their birth and riſing, which then might haue eaſily beene done. But you deale like an old beaten Foxe.</note> ſuppreſſed that a long time, hoping an agreement might bee obtained by the conuocation of a lawfull <hi>Prouinciall</hi> 
               <note n="(c)">Your cauſe, and the cauſe of your followers was ſo deſperate, that you hated a Synodal meeting, as much as the Diuell doth the Papiſts Croſſe.</note> 
               <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node.</hi> To which end the meanes of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation beganne to be vſed, but there was variance and iarring herein: when as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this hope <note n="(d)">Le vous croyrai, quan ie le verrai. I will beleeue you when I ſee it.</note> deceiued me, I preſented the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> ſpoken of. After the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whereof, none ſeemed to make any queſtion concerning the Articles of the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrancers</hi> opinion: and ſome <note n="(e)">Do you not (moſt reſpected) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what this crafty Foxe intends? The nets are ſpread, and ſnares laid, looke to him, moſt excellent Prince of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renge, and you great Aduocate and Embaſſadour, Lord <hi>Arſem,</hi> and my other good Lords, and famous defenders of the ancient reformed faith. Will you let things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſe with ſilence, and ſuffer a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique calumnie to bee faſtened on you, who ſtand in defence of Gods honour, and true Religion, and the good of the common-wealth? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, I beſeech you, that the ſtone is to be fitted to the ſquare, not the ſquare to the ſtone; and this muſt bee done while the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is new, before it waxe hard, leaſt the ruine of a faire building enſue.</note> plainely
<pb facs="tcp:21782:19"/>
and expreſſely (which now maintaine the opinion of the <hi>Contra-remonſtrancers</hi> with tooth and naile) ſaid, that ſuch a doctrine, as the <hi>Contra-remonſtrancers</hi> was then auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to bee, was <note n="(f)">You are the ſame man ſtill. But wee knowe what you aime at. Namely, that you may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a gappe to the <hi>Arminians</hi> for the committing of all impieties, luſts, rapes, &amp;c. &amp; hinder the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe &amp; peace of the <hi>Contra-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrancers</hi> who are the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and furtherers of the true Reformation.</note> neuer before this time heard off. Wee <note n="(g)">Obſerue the cunning &amp; wiles of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt (for why ſhould I not call this <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Prieſt</hi> of the Antichriſtian <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſo?) how ſtily he ſteales in, that he may murder, wrecke, and deſtroy. We reioiced ſayes he, becauſe he himſelfe was ioifull, and could not hold for laughter.</note> ſeemed to reioice, that there was no greater difficulty and trouble in the matter. The <hi>Remonſtrancers</hi> deſired a Copie, that their chiefe men might vpon conſideration conferre thereof: and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of all things might be made in a few dayes. After <note n="(a)">This was effected by this Machiuels leigerdemaine and cunning: and whileſt others leſſe intended the buſineſſe, he moſt deſirous to eſtabliſh his opinion, obtained what hee wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and reſtrained in our men, the liberty of conſcience, which he would not haue bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened. O father of miſchiefe!</note> theſe things it was determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that none ſhould bee troubled in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience about the foreſaid opinion, but that it be free <note n="(b)">Moſt diſſolute libertine, &amp; corrupt Atheiſt! How could this be poſsible in a matter of greateſt import, in a matter of faith, and a point ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary vnto ſaluation? But yet too few know that you are most expert in <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>contra,</hi> that you may ouerthrow both parts, and your ſelfe gaine by the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie.</note> for euery one both to thinke and teach further in the matter. <note n="(c)">Forbeare for ſhame to thruſt now this third time on vs the repitition of falſehoods, and vntruthes.</note> Wherein nothing elſe was done, but that which the Eccleſiaſticall perſons themſelues from the beginning of the Reformation both appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and agreed too, as well in the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Leiden</hi> before the Profeſſors of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie there, as alſo before many Preachers of Cities and townes, who were left in their places &amp; office, though it was euident, they were of the ſame opinion, and did teach the
<pb facs="tcp:21782:19"/>
ſame. The Queenes Maieſty alſo of Great <hi>Brittaine</hi> in two ſeuerall Letters liked &amp; counſelled the ſaid toleration: ſo that your Honours and Highneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes forenamed determination might by no meanes giue any iuſt cauſe of the lamentable ſchiſme of the preſent times: which tended to nothing elſe, but that the goſpellers (who were the greater part of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try) might be diuided among themſelues, and ſo weakened. As <note n="(d)">Here are Coleworts twice ſodden: yet they agree well with this old dotards ſtomack &amp; palat.</note> concerning your authoritie in and ouer cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and perſons Eccleſiaſticall, I proteſt, (as a thing neceſſary both for the ſeruices, and ſafety of your ſtate, as alſo for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of religion it ſelfe, and matters akinne thereto) I proteſt I ſay, that I haue alwaies defended it as the ſingular and moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie prerogatiue, and ſuperiority of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie: whoſe profit and gouernment to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, I am bound both by <note n="(e)">
                  <p>Pol qua opera iurato cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam tibi, vna opera adligem fugitivum canem agninis lactibus.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Truſt you? yes ſo I will, a ſtragling Dogge,</l>
                     <l>Haltred with tender Lambs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guttes to a clogge.</l>
                  </q>
               </note> oath and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Which <note n="(a)">
                  <p>The Prince knowes what <hi>Baſill</hi> ſayes; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>The reſpect due vnto Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men proceedes from God, and is to be referred to him.</p>
               </note> opinion from the beginning of the war, the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orenge</hi> &amp; the <hi>States</hi> alwaies auouched, and defended for good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Eccleſiaſticall perſons, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the contrary. I alwaies laboured to preſerue the authoritie of the <note n="(b)">
                  <hi>L'euento è ſpeſſo giudice non imperito delle coſe.</hi> Things are many times well iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of, by the euent.</note> companie of Ciuill iudges, as it did become mee, and according to the inſtruction of the ſaid <hi>Prince</hi> &amp; <hi>States,</hi> &amp; conformed the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to the rule of your determination, as it was both fitting &amp; moſt neceſſary for them to doe, for the peace &amp; good of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and free-Cities. The <note n="(c)">I would I might once ſee that performed indeede, which you profeſſe in words.</note> onely end of all things which vvere done by mee either in your meetings, or with the deputed Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates &amp; Generall-States, was the countries, and your honour, ſeruice, and good, and the enlarging of the laudable eſtimation of the ſame: wherein I alwaies vſed diſcretion &amp; moderation: ſo that I deſire, and from the bottom of my hart vnfainedly wiſh, that my ſucceſſour may for ſo many, or more yeares doe you as much good, &amp; (if it be poſſible) greater ſeruices, &amp; with your better approbation, and liking then I haue done. And I referre my ſelfe in as much as concernes my forementioned actions &amp; proceedings both in your mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,
<pb facs="tcp:21782:20"/>
and in the meetings of your deputies and the general States, to your owne <note n="(d)">The time wil come, when you wil wiſh you had eaten that word.</note> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie and iudgement, and the iudgement of your Commiſſaries, both thoſe who in generall, and thoſe who in particular haue had to doe in your companies and meetings for theſe 32. yeares laſt paſt: ſeauen or eight whereof doe yet ſuruiue in the alone citie of <note n="(e)">Take heed how you call honeſt men to witneſſe in your cracked cauſe: they are of the true &amp; refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med Religion, you neuer were ſo.</note> 
               <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> and either are, or haue been Burgomaſters of the ſame city, who haue bin acquainted with my actions and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe 25. yeares.</p>
            <p>If being ſlandered againſt reaſon, and ſet vpon with apparant lies (which by reaſon of a conſciouſneſſe of my daily and faithfull ſeruices I could not digeſt) I therefore ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reproued this impudence and ſlander a little too bitterly; I intreat, that humane <note n="(a)">Behold &amp; laugh to ſee the old dotard becom ſupplia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; brought on his knees: ſo a burnt childdreads the ſire. But what if he being a ſhameleſſe and lying fellow be too ſharpe in his reprehenſions, and therein exceede the limits of truth and modeſtie? May wee not then apply that in ſacred writ vnto him; <hi>Let him that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt be vniuſt ſtill, and he that is filthie be filthie ſtill?</hi> This is my opinion. For he is now grown old in his ſinnes and impieties.</note> infirmity and my olde age may heerein excuſe mee. Now if any thing, though <note n="(b)">What haue we heere? Is your bleating ſo ſoone changed into bellowing? Beware of him Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he purpoſes ſlaughter vnder a Lambs-skinne: yet ſeeing hee prouokes vs, let vs make a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick enquirie. <hi>Berneuell,</hi> why doe you make no conſcience ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to lie? Why doe you ſo mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly oppoſe the reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? Why are you an enemy to the Miniſters of your Countrey? why do you extenuate their authority? Why are you a hater &amp; hinderer of a future Synod? Why are you a traytor to your countrey? A priuate friend to the Spaniard? A hunter after glory &amp; wealth? A foe to the houſe of <hi>Naſsaue</hi> &amp; <hi>Orenge?</hi> A ſpend-thrift of the common Treaſure? A per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor of all good men, and fauourer of euill? Will you anſwere mee? Doe; but publickly: otherwiſe you ſhall be held as guiltie of all theſe crimes.</note> neuer ſo ſmall in buſineſſes either publique or priuate managed by mee, ſeeme liable to the reproofe of any, let that man openly ſpeake it, whoſoeuer he is, I craue no fauor. I preſume I ſhall conuince him, and in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable tearmes ſhew him his errour. It is true, that (according to a cuſtome receiued in tranſactions of leagues and peace) I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued gifts, more then the Lords condepu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with mee, though they were of great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation: and of this, publique notice was taken. But that either <note n="(c)">Hee that hath not learned to lie notably, fayles in confirming his owne cauſe. Sweare, forſweare: doe any thing ſooner then bewray your ſecrets.</note> before, or after the
<pb facs="tcp:21782:20"/>
Treatie, either directly or indirectly, either by my ſelfe or any proxie, I ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did take, or purpoſed to take any thing whatſoeuer more of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard or his complices, or had the leaſt dealing, communication, or treatie by my ſelfe, or by another with the Spaniard, or his confederates, without publike knowledge: that I ſolemnly auow to bee deuiſed, fained, and moſt contrary to the truth. Furthermore, it is knowne vnto you, that I my ſelfe motioned, and thought fit, that the gratuities before ſpoken of, which were beſtowed on me, ſhould bee kept for the publike good &amp; benefit: and ſome others there were, who approued not hereof.</p>
            <p>For the ſpace <note n="(a)">How oft haue you ſung this ſong? your repetition of the ſame things argues your memorie lies in your heeles.</note> of 32. yeeres (in which as <hi>Aduocate</hi> of the Countrey I beſtowed my paynes in your ſeruice) I was thus much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, that I was often intreated by the <note n="(b)">What doe you meane man? here is another groſſe abſurditie, you leaue out your great friend, the King of <hi>Spayne,</hi> whoſe right challenges the firſt place in your Catalogue: But you will ſay, it is conditioned bewtixt vs, that I ſhould not name him but vpon the rack. Excuſe me, I was not priuie to your crafty dealing.</note> King of <hi>France,</hi> by <hi>Eliz.</hi> Queene of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> both of famous and immortall memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: That I was often intreated by the King of great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> &amp; the K. of <hi>Sueland,</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector Palatine of <hi>Bradenburg,</hi> 
               <note n="(c)">It is ſuſpected you had too great dealings with him, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward through his meanes with the Spaniard.</note> the Elector of <hi>Colen,</hi> in diuers occurrences and buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes concerning them, to doe vnto them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Offices, and ſeruices. This I did being ſo deſired, either by their Letters, or Embaſſadors, or Commiſſaries, in ſuch matters as might be done with the benefite of the Countrey, or at leaſt without the loſſe and hindrance thereof. Namely and for example, I laboured in the Elector of <hi>Colens</hi> behalfe, that agreement might bee made betwixt him and the Arch-Dutcheſſe of <hi>Arſchot,</hi> the Counteſſe of <hi>Neeuweuaer,</hi> the Count and Counteſs of <hi>Solmes:</hi> euen to the finiſhing &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pounding of maters contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted among them; &amp; finally with the Count of <hi>Benthem</hi> for reſtitution of ſpeciall Offices of the Arch-biſhoprick of <hi>Colen.</hi> For which ſeruices hee both thanked me by Letters, &amp; preſented me with gifts: In like maner I helped other Princes, Counts, and forain Cities earneſtly requeſting mee thereto, by my good counſell. And thus much alſo was performed by me to Domeſtick Prouinces, Commanders, Counts, Lords, and moreouer to great ſocieties, and alſo to many priuate, and particular perſons, who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly &amp; of their owne accord acknowledged theſe my ſeruices, although I
<pb facs="tcp:21782:21"/>
neuer asked or demanded any of them any thing, directly or indirectly by my ſelfe, or by another.</p>
            <p>The <note n="(d)">Now he ſwels: Reader giue him the hearing. Now a ſtiffe gale filles his ſayles: lend him your beſt obſeruance. Here are great, maine matters of greateſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and import. Bragge is a good Dog ſtill.</note> chiefe matters which I did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme for the vnited Prouinces are theſe: <note n="(e)">Hee harpes againe vpon the ſame ſtring, you ſee he dotes: but he is old, we muſt pardon him, for he was a great bragger from his infancy, ſhortly he wil leaue it.</note> Firſt, fiue times I performed a Regall Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage, and in foure Embaſſages, the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and <note n="(a)">How the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed by his words, guidance, gouernment, and ſucceſſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold now he meditates.</note> direction of all things was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto me, and I my ſelfe ſpake to Kings, face to face. The firſt was in the yeere 85, wherein we firſt obtained of the Queene of <hi>England,</hi> the ayde of foure thouſand ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men, to rayſe the ſiege from <hi>Antwerpe:</hi> &amp; afterward a promiſe of 5000. foote-men, and a thouſand horſe-men (the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at <hi>Brill,</hi> and the Forts of <hi>Fluſhing</hi> and <hi>Rammekens</hi> not reckoned herein, becauſe they were places, and cities deliuered vp to her Maieſtie, as pledges, &amp; for ſecurities ſake) to be maintained in the time of warre.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Embaſſage was in the yeare 1598, to the King of <hi>France:</hi> a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was made by his Ma: of paying two millions, &amp; nine hundreth thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Florens to the States, within the ſpace of 4. yeares: &amp; furthermore, a ſecuritie concerning his Maieſties full and ſincere purpoſe to preſerue the good of theſe Dominions.</p>
            <p>In my third Embaſſage, performed the yeare premiſed, vnto the Queene of <hi>England,</hi> I <note n="(b)">
                  <hi>Paice vol figlio di padre crudele.</hi> We haue a ſweete ſonne of ſo cruella Father.</note> effected, that (howſoeuer the King of <hi>France</hi> had couenanted a league of peace with the K. of <hi>Spayne,</hi> &amp; the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke at <hi>Veruyns</hi>) neuertheles his Maieſty was moued to deferre and ſuſpend the like Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>In my fourth Embaſſage into <hi>England,</hi> a remiſſion of the third part of the exacted debts, eſteemed one and twenty hundred thouſand Florens was obtained of the Queenes Maieſty. So that it was agreed (much labour and difficultie praeceding) concerning the payment of foureſcore thouſand pounds Flemiſh, and the tearme of payment appointed for the halfe part <hi>(viz.)</hi> fortie hundred thouſand pound, was about twentie yeere, when in the compact made in the yeere 1585, wee couenanted to pay the whole
<pb facs="tcp:21782:21"/>
debt within the ſpace of foure yeares: and the terme, when wee ſhould paie the other halfe, was delaied and put off till another time.</p>
            <p>In my Embaſſage to the King of <hi>England</hi> at this day, I obtained, that the King gaue vs libertie to muſter two or three thouſand ſouldiers in <hi>Scotland</hi> for the benefit of the Prouinces, and alſo conſented that the King of <hi>France,</hi> for that yere ſhould lend vnto the Lords of the States-Generall a thouſand, three hundred, and fiftie pound: two thirds in his owne name, and one in the King of <hi>Great Brittaines</hi> name, to ſtrike off ſome of the debt, wherein the King of <hi>France</hi> was engaged to the King of <hi>Great-Brittaine:</hi> vpon ſight of which agreement, the King of <hi>France,</hi> in the yeere 1603, for the King of <hi>Great-Brittaines</hi> third, gaue the ſumme of three Millions of pounds, fiue hundred, and fiftie thouſand, and ſo much for himſelfe: ſo that the totall ſumme, was tenne millions of pounds, 350000.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of theſe fiue Regall Embaſſages, and tractates, it happened, that the forenamed Kings afforded to the States more then two hundred, &amp; fiue hundred thouſand pounds, from the payment wherof the confederated Prouinces (I hauing a principall hand therein) were diſcharged, and their Obligations ſurrended, as alſo their Citties and ſtrong holds laid to pledge.</p>
            <p>Another thing yet is this, that I for the moſt part, was a ſpeciall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer in our reſolutions, expeditions and warlike attempts, as well ſecret, as all others whatſoeuer, from the yeere 1558, vntill this time: and to further theſe things, as alſo to prouide all our purpoſes might bee effected, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and put in execution, <note n="(a)">Dare you only here bragge of your ſelfe, and your doings? where were the orders? where the ſtates? where <hi>Graue Maurice?</hi>
               </note> I thirtie <note n="(b)">How oft will you hitte a moſt Martiall Prince in the teeth with this? Doe you thinke hee could not haue managed the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires without your helpe? Yea it is to bee wiſhed that ſometimes you had beene abſent when you were not.</note> ſeuerall times, eyther accompanied his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence, or mette him in his Campe, and there I continued ſometimes a moneth, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more, or <note n="(c)">
                  <hi>That was when you were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, for it is moſt certaine,</hi> Sempree longiunto ne vn medeſimo ſoggetto l'inſolentia con la timidita.</note> leſſe according to diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent neceſſitie of buſineſſes then in hand.</p>
            <p>A third thing is, that I was a chiefe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and hinderance (with policie, with paynes, and waight of Reaſon) now more then thirtie yeeres <note n="(d)">Would you perſwade this alſo vnto me? but be it, that you were ſuch an one then: <hi>Quantum mutatus ab illo: You are now ſtrangely altered.</hi>
               </note> that the propoſitions, concerning peace-making with the Spany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard and his confederats, might not take ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo long as they perſeuered to inſiſt in
<pb facs="tcp:21782:22"/>
their pretended courſes Eſpecially becauſe they auouched that the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of theſe Prouinces were their ſubiects. But after they renounced this claime, and pronounced that they accounted the Prouinces free, to which neither in their owne behalfes, nor in the behalfe of their heires, they made no chalenge, and were content to determine of matters vvith the States vpon theſe tearmes: and a meeting begunne vpon theſe tearmes might ſeeme to promiſe a diuine, honourable, and ſecure diſpatch of all things (by the interceſſion of the Embaſſadours of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> Great <hi>Britaine, Denmarke,</hi> and diuers of the Electors and Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> ſpeciall friends and confederates to theſe Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,) with ſingular difficultie, labour, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and conſtancie I beſtirred my ſelfe to obtaine the fore-ſpoken end of matters, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the time all things were quite finiſhed: wherevpon that <note n="(a)">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſe are ſure truthes, which we may build vpon. But why did you change the warre againſt a foraine enemie into ciuill warre, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the followers of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? for this was no leſſe difficult, chargeable, and I would not blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die too, then the other.</note> difficult, bloudy and chargeable Belgicke warre was ceaſed now and appeaſed for ten yeeres.</p>
            <p>A fourth thing is, that I was one of the principall, by whoſe meanes the dangerous and pernicious plots of the <note n="(b)">The ſame thing now ten times repeated.</note> Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and his complices plottes were auoided and defeated, and of thoſe who prouided that the confederated Prouinces might not bee ruined by his two yeeres vnfortunate gouernement, and come into the Spaniards power.</p>
            <p>A fift thing is, that about the <note n="(c)">Nothing but the ſame ſong ſtill, <hi>Parret?</hi> Repeat it a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, but to your ſelfe alone.</note> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my fore-named Office, to wit of my being Aduocate of the Countrey, when all things were in great confuſion, &amp; the very name of the Lords of the States was hated: within the compaſſe of a few yeeres, matters were brought in better caſe, ſo farre forth that there was correſpondence, agreement, and loue betwixt the Lords of the States, his Excellencie as Gouernour, the Companies of the grand and Prouinciall Councell, the treaſurers, and accountants, and the Officialls and Magiſtrates of cities, and common-weales.</p>
            <p>A ſixt thing is, <note n="(d)">Stil he ſtirs a ſtinking puddle.</note> That all the heads, Admiralls, Commanders, Adminiſters of the principall Offices of warre, Gouernours of horſemen, Captaines, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, ſouldiers, which earned pay either by ſea, or by land, all theſe, I ſay,
<pb facs="tcp:21782:22"/>
acknowledged the Lords the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> as pay-maſters of their ſtipends, ſwore faith and obedience vnto them, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured his Excellence as Captaine Generall in commanding the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch things, as the Lords the States determined: that euery one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended his Office and place hee was called vnto. And moreouer, that for many yeeres the <note n="(a)">Was not this alwaies oppoſed? You cannot ſhew any preſcription to the contrary: Fret if you pleaſe, yet will we haue what we wiſh.</note> Eccleſiaſticall perſons acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged your Honours, for their lawfull and chiefe Gouernour. So that for the ſpace of well-nigh thirtie yeeres, in which the Lords the States had ſomtimes threeſcore troopes of horſemen, ſeuen hundred companies of footmen, and more then an hundred Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines making vvarre by ſea, there vvas neuer any <note n="(b)">And now how great muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are there among brethren? If you then made peace among others, why are you now your ſelfe ſeditious? Haply this comes into your head for defence of your <hi>Arminians.</hi> Great tranquillitie, is not procured, with great hurly-burly. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. God knowes who is authour of all theſe ſtirres and euills.</note> diſſenſion, rebellion, or treacherie among them. And the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaltie vvas kept in reſt and quietneſſe, &amp; due obedience to their lawful Gouernors. The matter certainely was ſtrange and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, vvorthy our obſeruation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, eſpecially in nations ſo different. For, beſides ſtrangers, we vſed at thoſe times (either as intire companies, or otherwiſe diuided and beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed) <hi>Germans, Frenchmen, Engliſh, Scots, Switzers, Wallons.</hi> Whoſoeuer ſhall certainely weigh theſe things, and hath read the ancient times, and ſhall conſider what things haue beene done vnder vs for theſe fourteene yeeres, and ſo onward, (while the warre continued) vnder the Spaniard, they ſhall finde that we haue iuſt occaſion to render Almighty God praiſe and thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing therefore. Many men famous for their power, dignity and learning, haue highly commended this matter: And thereby the Lords the States, and his Excellence haue wonne much credit, praiſe and authoritie not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the inhabitants of the confederated Prouinces, all neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Kings, Electors, Princes Common-wealthes, and people farre remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but euen with the Spaniards themſelues, and their accomplices and fellowes.</p>
            <p>A <note n="(a)">Theſe things were forgotten by this time. Therefore your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition is ſeaſonable.</note> ſeuenth thing is, and which muſt not be accounted for the leaſt benefite, that I haue alwaies beene a principall and daily inſtrument ſo farre to increaſe and augment the credit of the Lords of the States, that whereas for many yeeres, before
<pb facs="tcp:21782:23"/>
I tooke vpon me this Office, the States had no credite with men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by monies might be taken vp in their names, and by their conſents, and vpon the morgaging of their reuenewes, and penſions: and therefore great ſtore of monie was to be taken vp in the Receiuers and Treaſurers owne names, and vpon their owne credit: for which monies for the ſpace of ten or twelue yeere there was a yeerely penſion of twelue in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth to be paid: and moreouer two for the procuring thereof. <note n="*">The Latine Caſtigator hath obſerued, that the Dutch copy is corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and faulty here, and in diuers places elſewhere, and it ſhalbe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient once to haue ſhewed ſo much. Whether the Author or the Printer is to be blamed therefore he doth not determine.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That yeere in which I vndertooke the Aduocates Office, the generall Treaſurers euery fift or ſixt yeere gaue vp their accounts. Some of the Exactors of the Commons goods and riches, theirs in the fourth yeere: and ſome of the Treaſurers of the Church-goods and others, theirs in a longer time, and many more yeares. Which faſhion was thus farre amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that afterwards accounts of the Commons good were giuen vp e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery halfe yeere, and of other goods euery yeere at the furtheſt.</p>
            <p>When I entred into my office, foureſcore hundred thouſand Florens could ſcarce be raiſed in the generalitie for maintaining the charges of warre, by reaſon of the penury and want of the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland:</hi> but at this preſent they pay more at the leaſt then <note n="(b)">Tell me, I pray, whoſe purſe is filled with theſe thouſands? vpon what vſe are they beſtowed? That you and yours may be enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereby, the ſubiects beggered? O <hi>Holland.</hi> Where is thy liberty? For what purpoſe didſt thou ſuffer ſo many grieuances and annoiances in that moſt lamentable warre? O <hi>Holland,</hi> who beſtowed fatherly direction vpon thee, and vſed a motherly care and compaſsion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee? Thou wert reſerued to a Step-mothers brawles, deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to pillage and ſpoile, left deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late by the luſt and rapines af miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants: wert thou therefore pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> claw, that thou mighteſt bee trampled vnder the feet of the <hi>Arminian</hi> Goates and Hogges? and now ſhouldeſt periſh more lamentably in durt and mudde, then thou couldeſt at that time in the aire. Plucke vp a good heart, reſume thy ſtrength, acquite thy ſelfe of theſe enemies. Let them periſh, who ſeeke thy deſtruction.</note> two and fortie hundred thouſand pounds. But heere it is to be obſerued, that the coſts of the warre for theſe thirtie two yeeres, wherein I continued in Office, were ſo great and extreame, that you cannot chuſe for the preſent, but get more by the charges of <hi>Holland</hi> alone and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> then in the yeere 1586. could bee gathered both for the charges of the generalitie, as alſo for the particular charges of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland;</hi> namely, more then two millions of Florens, euery yeere. Which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, beſides the fore-mentioned for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie two hundreth thouſand pounds doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue &amp; are paid out of the Countreys yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rents. And howſoeuer it is more fitting to burden the Countrey, then quite to loſe
<pb facs="tcp:21782:23"/>
it: yet wiſedome and prouidence willes vs to obſerue (as the Aſſemblies of the grand and prouinciall Councell, and the Maſters of accounts ſhowed by writing in the yeere 1604.) while the burdens and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances exceede the reuenewes, the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces muſt neceſſarily at laſt bee vndone and ruined: and if theſe laſt ten yeeres we had beene charged with ſo great coſts, as wee were theſe ten fore-going yeeres; the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland</hi> onely vvould haue amounted by this time to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſumme of foure millions of Florens. Which euill (that I may let paſſe in ſilence other dangers and troubles as well foreſeene and knowne) the <note n="(a)">Which was the beginning of Ciuil warre, accidentally at least.</note> truce lately made, ſalued, and helped.</p>
            <p>And my good Lords: I had almoſt <note n="(b)">He acknowledges his memory failes him. It is well yet that hee will once confeſſe his fault. And if her in he had not forgot himſelfe, he would haue amplified &amp; extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his wealth till hee had beene hoarſe againe.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, that ſome ill-willers both to you and me, enuie and repine at my eſtate, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. I would haue you thinke that it is neither ſo great, nor ſo ſubiect to enuie, as their words and ſpeeches make it. I profeſſe that I had by <note n="(a)">This is good, that this old <hi>Beldame</hi> is brought vpon the ſtage now the ſecond time. Bleſſe the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> ſaue you goody-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, ſaue your Ladies hippe.</note> my wife (whom I married <note n="(b)">Therefore you were married in your twenty ſeuenth yeere: and the common-wealth lost nothing thereby.</note> forty three yeeres ſince) ſo much goods and lands, as might honeſtly haue maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me. And my ſtipend and practiſe at that time (for I was an <hi>Aduocate</hi> of the Court) ſo great, that without controuerſie they yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were worth <note n="(c)">This is a large reckoning, but you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid leſt ſome-body call you to account: for if you yeeld you then got foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, you will now willingly grant, you haue fortie thouſand yeerely by your office; your <hi>Aduocates</hi> office I meane: and ſo much by the Seale, twice as much by being of the Councell, foure times as much by your practiſe, and ten times as much by nimming and iuggling. It is no maruell if theſe trickes made you as rich as <hi>Croeſus.</hi> Eſpecially if we reckon herein the gifts of Kings and Princes beſtowed vpon you: and namely of your ſpeciall friend the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </note> foure thouſand Florenes. For I was not one of the leaſt <note n="(d)">You would rather then your life haue called your ſelfe the greateſt, but your writing erred for modeſties ſake.</note> practiſers
<pb facs="tcp:21782:24"/>
among the <hi>Aduocates,</hi> and we were but eight in all. In the beginning of the yeere ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſeuen <note n="(e)">Repetition is a Rhetoricall fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, wherein you are very cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> my firſt imploiment was in <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdam.</hi> Out of the wages allowed by the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with other veiles I could wel-nigh main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine my family, being now made richer by two children onely.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, I can truely demonſtrate, that from the ſaid ſeuenty ſeuenth yeere, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the 1616. yeere full out, both I and my <note n="(f)">Your louely <hi>Helena</hi> ſhowes her ſelfe now the third time. And take heed leſt too often: for if wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men keep not their houſes, and dwell apart by themſelues, they are quickly corrupted. Yea, euen old ones too, leſt you haply ſhould deceiue your ſelfe.</note> wife for our <note n="(g)">Marchants, Factors, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are oftentimes rich men.</note> parts, as alſo for our kinsfolkes and acquaintance parts, for our ſelues, and for our children haue poſſeſſed by inheritance, and attained by lawfull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and title, more then eight hundred meaſured acres, or according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of <hi>Holland,</hi> foure <note n="(h)">In the higher or lower <hi>Welue,</hi> or in the <hi>Duinen,</hi> or <hi>Maeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke,</hi> or in <hi>Waterland,</hi> of which ſide will you turne it?</note> hundred acres of ground; and for goodes mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, more then two thouſand Florens yearely: a faire houſe in the Citie of <hi>Delfe,</hi> and in the open fields ſome houſes beſides, and ſome thouſands of Florens in hand, and preſently tendered.<note n="(i)">The neereſt of kindred to your wife were Brewers, and had faire houſes.</note> 
               <note n="(b)">
                  <hi>Haec &amp; Pylaea nouit &amp; tu Hygias.</hi> Your ſelfe and your wife know this, let others ſpeake of it.</note> Moreouer, that I wonne out of the water and mudde more acres of ground (then the forenamed) longer agoe then forty yeeres paſt, and encloſed them with bankes and hedges round about. That <note n="(c)">
                  <p>Heere was ſtrange practiſe: learne of him, Reader, how thou maiſt grow rich? Yet I doe not giue thee ſuch counſell. For you ſee the old prouerbe is verefied in this Miſer;
<q>
                        <l>La conuoitiſe croiſt ſi les richeſſes croiſſent.</l>
                        <l>Et de nouueaux acqueſts nouueaux deſirs ſurnaiſſent.</l>
                     </q>
But let the Aduocate remember what Chriſt thunders out in the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list. <hi>It is more eaſie for a Camell to paſſe through the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enter into the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> at the ſame time I bought &amp; ſold, as well out of the goods I had by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as thoſe which I bought at a price, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eight hundred thouſand Florens. I <note n="(d)">It is poſſible, your ſelfe did not, but others for you by whoſe marchandiſe you gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>more wealthy.</note> neuer dealt in marchandize: but according
<pb facs="tcp:21782:24"/>
to the cuſtome of my anceſtors, I imployed all my ſtocke in husbandry and tillage. And for all this, I brought into the great &amp; gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Eaſt-Indian Company (in executing whereof I beſtowed foure-yeeres paines pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely to extenuate the <note n="(e)">Ah, ſpare your friends. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by their meanes thoſe croſſe-bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ring pieces of gold doe ſhine i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your cheſt: I ſay both thoſe grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pieces, and thoſe little ones, which are neither round nor broad, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ponderous, and weighty.</note> 
               <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Portugals</hi> wealth) aboue the number of fiue hundred thouſand Florens, by vvhich ſumme fourteene ſhippes might bee ſet out: that by this meanes I might not onely be thought a counſailer, but an <note n="(f)">A helper to your ſelfe, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the filling of your owne purſe, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were alwaies.</note> helper, and ſuccourer in ſome meaſure, in all thoſe ſtraites and difficulties, which I did foreſee. Although my eſtate then were great and rich, yet in my opinion, none of you ought to repine at it: and yet further, I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy profeſſed in an open congregation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you all, and now heere againe repeate it, in this my <note n="(g)">
                  <p>I my ſelfe ſuffer with you and pitie you: but I wiſh you t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> comfort your ſelfe with the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membrance of that in the Poet:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Rara antecedentem ſceleſtum</l>
                           <l>Deſeruit pede poena claudo.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Wee ſeldome vice ſo nimble-footed finde,</l>
                           <l>That her beſt ſpeed, leaues puniſhment behinde.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
Or this in <hi>Syneſius;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. The iuſtice of God goeth ſlowe and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly: but for the moſt part it recompenceth the ſlackneſſe of iudgement vvith the heauineſſe thereof.</p>
               </note> diſtreſſe (which hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued more now then eight <note n="(a)">Endure it ſtoutly and couragiouſly, ſhortly you ſhall be cooped vp, and ſuffer vnder a hand that ſhall take vengeance for all your offences.</note> monethes) I tooke an account of my goods, &amp; I found, that I muſt bee conſtrained to ſell ſo much goods, as are worth ſixtie, or ſeuenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Florens, that I may <note n="(b)">That you may leaue them free from charge, you will purchaſe damnation to your ſelfe.</note> leaue no charge vpon my children and heires. And this I had rather my ſelfe ſee done in my life time, then my children ſhould bee enforced thereto after my death. Yet thinke not, I pray you, that I am growne weaker in my eſtate by any ill husbandry of my owne: but by <note n="(c)">
                  <p>Why doe you complaine then? Why like an Hypocrite doe you deceiue the mightie States and Orders? You pretend affliction was added to affliction, and preſently forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your ſelfe, you confeſſe you became richer then before you were. What hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible lies are theſe? Durſt you ſpeake ſuch incongruities in the Aſſembly, and ſight of the States! but your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe priuiledges you in all things.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>A quel effect, à quel enorme vice,</l>
                     <l>Ne pousſes tu o inaudite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice?</l>
                     <l>To what effect, to what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normous vice,</l>
                     <l>Puſheth thee not vnheard of Auarice?</l>
                  </q>
               </note> ſucceeding foure ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:21782:25"/>
perſons, (whoſe ſole heire I was) and certaine others, where I had both coheires, and vnderwent ſome coſts alſo: further, I bought out more goods with coſts and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances thereto belonging: moreouer, ſome things I compaſſed in with ſea-walles, others I mended with money tooke vpon truſt. Now, if it ſtand with your pleaſure to make an enquirie into your ſubiects goods, and taxe them; I for my part eaſily <note n="(d)">How would it terrifie you, if the States ſhould ſay ſo much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you?</note> aſſent thereto: for I am certaine, that thoſe, who in the generall ſubſidie in the yeare 1599. eſteemed not all the goods they poſſeſſed, worth fiftie, or at moſt ſixty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Florens, now boaſt, that they are two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fould richer then I am: and yet the ſame <note n="(e)">Worſhipfull friends, will you ſilently heare this defamation? Behold, that he may cleere him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee accuſes you, and ſawcily inſults ouer you. Yea hee inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates that you gotte your goods vniuſtly, that vnrighteouſly you taxed others, that for hatred and grudges, you ſubuerted the lawes of Aequity, and Iuſtice: are not theſe manifeſt ſlanders? the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations of a Sycophant? haue a care I pray you of your good name. For if he weaken or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw you, who ſtand ſtoutly by your ſelues for the ancient refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, what can wee hope for? <hi>LL. civiles pro vobis. L. vlt. C. de Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> parties the ſaid yeare vpon a ſpleene numbred me among thoſe, who paid moſt, and were taxed at two hundred thouſand Florens. The makers of ſeditions, and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous libels and bookes, two whereof, (the one being called <hi>A neceſſarie diſcourſe,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>The practiſe of the Spaniſh Councell</hi>) are fraught with manifeſt and notorious lies, falſhoods &amp; calumnies, <note n="(a)">You cannot ſo eaſily acquitte your ſelfe, truſt mee: and many things which thoſe bookes ſpeake of, may be proued by records and ſufficient witneſſes: but this care I leaue vnto others, and therfore will not reply vnto your new and trifling allegations. And I perſwade my ſelfe I ſhall doe ſo with your good leaue.</note> ſo farre forth, as they ſpeake of my actions; &amp; ſay, that I haue fat offices. I anſwer, this is vſually compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by long and truſtie ſeruice, to the whole Kingdome, the Prouince, and the common wealth. My Predeceſſour in the firſt yeare of his office, was made keeper of the great Seale; vnder which Seale, at that time the
<pb facs="tcp:21782:25"/>
beſtowing of places in the warres (which was a very gainefull matter) paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: which in my time was not ſo, neither was the cuſtodie thereof wholly committed vnto me ſooner then after the fifteenth yeare of my <hi>Aduocate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> place. But ſince the keeping of the Seale fell vnto me, ſome ten conuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances in all buſineſſes thereunto belonging paſſed vnder the ſaid Seale, by which I <note n="(b)">Neuertheleſſe, your ſeruants were enriched thereby.</note> made no gaine, not a <hi>Doit,</hi> which might benefit me. The Vice-maiſters place of the fees hath not allowed one halfe penny for ſtipend: and thus farre I could gaine but a little. In the yeare 1586. you named me for keeper of the <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> and ouerſeer of the <hi>Rolles:</hi> and when afterwards the Lord of <hi>Nortwick,</hi> and Preſident <hi>Nicholas</hi> were dead, you beſtowed vpon me (as the onely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuer) the ſame ſtate with ioynt conſent. And I perſwade my ſelfe, that I haue done good ſeruice therein, both to the <note n="(c)">And in the firſt place, to your ſelfe and your owne purſe.</note> country &amp; the parties which had ought to doe there. The ſet ſtipend thereof amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to an hundred and eight Florens yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And although the ſtipends of others the like, were now growen three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold greater, then they were before the war, yet would not I <note n="(a)">You needed not: for you paid your ſelfe.</note> intreat you for any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: moreouer, the profits are vncertaine. In place of this condition my Predeceſſor was ouerſeer of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Leiden,</hi> and of the priuy Councell of <hi>Rhineland.</hi> For my <note n="(b)">He is already worthy to bee ſainted, the Pope will ſhortly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonize him.</note> appearances in the meetings of Aſſemblies deputed by you, for theſe 32. yeares and vpwards, and for all the buſineſſes wherein I dealt with his <hi>Excellence,</hi> I receiued no ſtipend: neither receiued I any for my appearances in the Councell of the general States in your name, all the time forementioned: although I had more then <note n="(c)">He counts very accurately: it ſeemeth he noted it in his table bookes.</note> twentie fiue ſeuerall times a <note n="(d)">Yea and rich performance too.</note> promiſe of recompence from you. How falſly and ſhameleſſely then theſe libellers dare ſpeake, and write that which you know to bee a tale, I thinke it worth my paines heere briefly to ſhow. That queſtions were <note n="(e)">They did not then indeede be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to be firſt moued, but to be firſt publiſhed; to ſtirre vp the people, and ſubuert the Countrey. Confeſſe your fault and mend it.</note> firſt moued touching <hi>Religion</hi> after the truce, is without queſtion falſe; forasmuch as in the doctrine concerning <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> and the appendices thereto, there was a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie
<pb facs="tcp:21782:26"/>
of queſtions and opinions too a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reformed Doctours, not onely in the time of warre, but before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof. And they were alwaies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, who taught the ſame, vnto <note n="(f)">Prouided that the truth, which is immutable, and to which we claue, might not bee preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. The <hi>Arminians</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers from the beginning, and your ſelfe the forge of all lies.</note> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety and edification. Now from the yeare 74. queſtions were moued accordingly as order required, in theſe Prouinces; my good Lord and Maiſter, the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> of pious memory, and the Lords and States a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerring that it was a <note n="(g)">You affirme this ſo often, that it is loathſome and odious, but you doe not proue it: Who ſees not then your preposterous dealing?</note> part of their office and power to make <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> lawes and orders; as thoſe, in whom the lawfull <hi>ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy</hi> reſided, according to a receiued cuſtom in all Kingdomes, Prouinces, Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, and Cities, which haue entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a reformation againſt the Idolatry, <note n="(a)">This you ſaid well; for the <hi>Arminians</hi> haereſie is the moſt dangerous haereſie: and ſo you confound your ſelfe.</note> hereſie, and <note n="(b)">You are the moſt vſurping <hi>Tyrant,</hi> worſe then the <hi>Pope:</hi> and if you will, I will ſtraight way proue what I ſay, <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
               </note> tyrannie of the <hi>Papacie:</hi> as appeares by his <note n="(c)">Eyther you vnderſtand them not, or haue corrupted them; for the words expreſſe not ſo much, as you of your owne head deuiſe: conſider better of them.</note> Ordinances and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees then made, and afterward ſent from place to place to the Nobles and free-Cities in the yeare 1610. which is alſo gathered out of the <note n="(d)">If you had cited the text, you had brought a teſtimonie againſt your ſelfe: for, <hi>ſomewhat lies vnder the rinde of the words.</hi>
               </note> Ordinances made in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland</hi> in the yeare 1582. &amp; 1591. In <hi>Zeland</hi> the ſame yeare 1591. In <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricke</hi> in the yeare 1590. Laſtly, in <hi>Gronland,</hi> and the neighbouring places in the yeare .1595.</p>
            <p>Your Honours and Excellencies knowe very well, that I, not onely before the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie concerning peace, but while the treatie laſted, and alwaies afterward, <note n="(e)">
                  <p>Heare what I will ſay, but in a hidden language and knowne to your ſelfe alone amongſt the Hollanders. <hi>Paga de muchos ſeruicios puede vn hombre hazer, mas para vn buen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcio pagar todos los Dios ſon meneſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doe you ſpeake theſe things from your heart? or without fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, cunning fraude and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie?</p>
               </note> ſeriouſly laboured both publikely and otherwiſe, that the Spaniard, and his allies might in no ſort be credited: and that I openly profeſſed, that it was vncredible, that the Spaniard ſhould euer forget thoſe iniuries, which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued we did vnto them: and that <note n="(f)">This it is to bee a man of note and famous: let the patriots marke it.</note> wee
<pb facs="tcp:21782:26"/>
therefore ſhould take the like courſe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I alwaies <note n="(g)">Your diligence is commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if loue and affection cauſed it: now ſeeing it is cleane contrary, it muſt bee ſcorned and hiſſed at.</note> ſollicited, that the value of the <note n="(h)">Haue you not forgotten what befell vnto <hi>Sixtus 5.</hi> your friend? He, when hee had impoſed new contributions at Rome, receiued this anſwere, <hi>Mi aſciguo inan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zi che il ſole ſi venda.</hi> May not the Hollanders iuſtly make the ſame reply vnto you, <hi>Qui a o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reilles, oye et entende.</hi>
               </note> contributions ſhould not onely be continued, but increaſed; and that of the profits thereof by better husbanding might be made the vttermoſt: ſo that the truce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either broken or finiſhed, wee might proceed to warre better <note n="(i)">Nótre ànon eſt bien oreilié, mais il n' entendra pas cela.</note> prouided, then when the truce begun to be made.</p>
            <p>They alleage in their booke a certaine anſwer giuen by the generall-States to the Arch-Duke <hi>Erneſte</hi> in the yeare 1594: but they adde not that I was the authour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as likewiſe of ſix at leaſt of the ſame kind, which were directed to the Lord of <hi>Reydt,</hi> the Count <hi>Mandeſcheyt, Charles Nurſell,</hi> and many more, and afterward in progreſſe of time ſent ouer to them.</p>
            <p>By theſe things the libellers may ſeeme onely to expect this, viz. that wee ſhould haue continued the war, either till <hi>Brabant, Flanders,</hi> and the reſidue of the Prouinces had beene conquered, and ſo haue come to vs as a refuge: or till the Spaniard had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our Prouinces, and brought them in the ſame caſe, wherein others then vvere. Which <note n="(b)">And prouiſion was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that you fainted not before you had done.</note> buſineſſe requires many words, much ſpeech: as alſo, that wee haue made ſundry chargeable expeditions into <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Flanders:</hi> and howſoeuer the inhabitants, and cities there were warned and intreated to giue a peremptorie anſwer concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a mutuall vnion with vs: yet not any one citie, nay not any one man of note, ſhewed or declared that he would be on our partie. And they are compelled, who belong vnto the other Prouinces, whether they dwell heere or elſe where, to beleeue &amp; acknowledge, that the <note n="(c)">Yours eſpecially in ſowing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: you can make nothing elſe good, whatſoeuer you boaſt of.</note> honeſtie, courage and conſtancie of our men (eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland</hi>) hath beene, and is yet at this day very commodious vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21782:27"/>
               <note n="(d)">He ſpeakes truely heere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning you, (great and mighty States) you were alwayes indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the matter, if I except the Aduocate and one or two more-He is the troubler hereof.</note> You neuer denied a lawfull (but not partiall and diuided) and equall Prouinciall Synod vnto <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> but rather imploied your paines to procure one. But a <note n="(e)">Who made that Queſtion? Or who vſed thoſe arguments by way of oppoſing it? was it not your ſelfe, and your <hi>Arminians?</hi> Out yee Popiſh knaues, ſonnes of darkeneſſe, and night ſhadows, you flie the light, and dare not ſhew your ſelues in publick, and defend your fopperies in an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Aſſemblie. Hence it is that you ſeeke ſtarting holes, and by paſſages, and deuiſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to truth. But the time is neere wherein all <hi>Arminians</hi> ſhall be repreſſed, and reſtrayned. Beſtirre your ſelfe and act your part (moſt excellent Prince <hi>Maurice</hi>) I moſt humbly pray you: and you my Lords the mightie States, beſtirre your ſelues: buckle to it, Maſter <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> moſt decre and neere, both by reaſon of one common and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall language, and alſo daylie acquaintance and familiaritie: and you <hi>Francis Gomar,</hi> whoſe care of, and for vs, ſtill ſhewes it ſelfe: you <hi>Anthony Smoutius, Vrſine, Salig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacus, Dammannus, de Lauignus Ellerus,</hi> and al the remainder of the Miniſters of Gods word, beſtirre your ſelues I ſay, and defend our ancient Reformation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince theſe Innouators, banniſh and roote them out from among you, appoint and publiſh a Nationall Synod at Dort, or any where elſe, which the <hi>Arminians</hi> doe more hate, then the Owle the light of the Sunne. I for my part, if it bee fitting, will ſtrengthen and prepare my ſelfe therein againſt them with reaſons, obſeruations, hiſtories, and teſtimonies of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to my vtmoſt power.</note> queſtion was made, by what meanes this might bee ordained in ſo great diſſenſion &amp; diſagreement: ſo that it might tend (which was the principall matter) to the benefit of the Church and Country, and quietneſſe of the Comminaltie. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely there is a maine difference betwixt the meetings of particular parts of one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, or foure parts thereof, and a Synode of a whole and entire Prouince; betwixt the times of ſchiſme and diſſenſion, &amp; the times of Peace and Concord.</p>
            <p>Men talke much of the Commiſſions, and Oathes as well of the Chiefetaines, as of the militarie route: but it is euident, that ſuch eyther haue not ſeene, or at leaſt vnderſtand not theſe things; ſeeing both the words and meaning thereof are much different from that which they vndiſcreetely coyne. They iudge of others according to their owne falſe, peruerſe, and lying hearts. They doe manifeſtly contradict the truth (I conteſt your knowledge) when they ſay Maſter <hi>Francis Francken</hi> of pious memorie was Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate of the Countrie. For you know that he had no publick office in your Aſſembly, but that he was a Counſellor and Penſioner
<pb facs="tcp:21782:27"/>
of <hi>Goud:</hi> afterward, leauing that office hee ſupplied the Aduocates place for ſome yeers and interceded for both Councels, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward hee was made a Counſailor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>It is conſpicuous that they forbeare to ſpeake the truth, when they report that I ſaid to his Excellency, and alſo to ſome Preachers, that I had made <note n="(a)">
                  <p>Your exception againſt the matter controuerted giues not ful ſatisfaction; or the originall, which is writte in Dutch is falſe. Neuertheleſſe, when he ſtriues moſt to excuſe it, he plurges him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into more errors. I will briefely therefore, ſince it is a matter of moment, lay downe, what is here ſpoken. The Label<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſay and proue by <hi>Barneuelts</hi> owne words, that <hi>Vtenbogart</hi> was made an <hi>Arminian</hi> by him. <hi>Barneuelt</hi> denies he did any ſuch thing, becauſe forſooth, he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nothing concerning the point of Praedeſtination eyther of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius</hi> or <hi>Vtenbogarte.</hi> Now I demand, if he haue ſatisfied the obiection, and approued himſelf to be as cleere, as if he were waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with milke. Hee that hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brayne, ſees hee is not well in his wittes, if hee thinkes as hee writes; or elſe fooliſh altogether, if hee thinke one thing and write another: eſpecially, ſince the matter in queſtion is the crime of Hereſie, and the villany of ſeducing in a cauſe concerning ſaluation. But what lettes, why the Aduocate may not be ſaid to haue made the Preacher <hi>Vtenbogart</hi> an <hi>Arminian?</hi> Becauſe he affirmes that he learned nothing of the ſaid partie: yea, this is rather a ſolid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the matter, eſpecially ſince it is vſed for an excuſe. To ſpeake more plainly, <hi>Barneuelt</hi> is an <hi>Arminian: Vtenbogart</hi> is an <hi>Arminian</hi> too: the one made the other an <hi>Arminian.</hi> Now the queſtion is who was the ſeducer? I, that I may end the controuerſie, will frame an hypotheticall Syllogiſme, ſuch an one as <hi>Cicero</hi> concerning <hi>Milo</hi> and <hi>Clodius.</hi> Eyther <hi>Vtenbogart</hi> ſeduced <hi>Barneuelt,</hi> or <hi>Barneuelt Vtenbogart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>Vtenbogart</hi> did not ſeduce <hi>Barneuelt,</hi> therefore <hi>Barneuelt</hi> ſeduced <hi>Vten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bogart.</hi> The hypotheſis makes the propoſition of an vngainſayable truth: the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is affirmed by <hi>Berneuelt</hi> himſelfe. The concluſion then is, <hi>Berneuelt</hi> was the ſeducer.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vtenbogart</hi> an <hi>Arminian.</hi> This I ſaid, that I, when <hi>Herma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Herbartes</hi> cauſe about 26 yeeres ſince was handled before me at the <hi>Haigh,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things it was declared that he would not profeſſe the Almightie God to be the Author of ſinne, that I, as I ſaid, warned <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenbogarte</hi> returning to his houſe, that this buſineſſe of praedeſtination, condemning, or reprobating, would ſtirre vp great troubles, as a matter that became not Chriſtians, and was repugnant to my mind and thouſands more: in which minde and opinion, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed I had perſiſted from the yeare 1568. and therefore that I had learned nothing either of <hi>Arminius</hi> or <hi>Vtenbogarte</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this point.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21782:28"/>Tis falſe alſo, that I made them Burgoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Aldermen, and common Counſellers in free-cities-who fitted my humour: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things were the leaſt part of my care. In fine, that being intreated thereto by ſome few cities, I mentioned the matter to his Excellence. But his Excellence herein chiefly vſed the counſell of the Preſidents, <hi>Vander Myle, Wingaerd, Inioſſa</hi> and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours.</p>
            <p>Tis a meere cogge, that the King of <hi>France</hi> offered by his Embaſſadours the reliefe of an hundred thouſand crownes monethly. As this alſo was feigned that the charges of the warre ſurpaſſed the ſumme of ſeuen millions of crownes. In like manner, that three millions of crownes were requeſted of the King of <hi>France.</hi> It is alſo a plaine lie, that I gaue vnto Preſident <hi>Ianyn,</hi> and <hi>Buſanual</hi> ſome thouſands of Florenes. As yee likewiſe know it to be a fained tale, that I had power of diſpoſing an hundred twenty thouſand Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renes yeerely. I had onely in lieu of my extraordinary expences, and the trouble of making correſpondence within, and without the Countrey and the adiacent places, fiue hundred Florenes yeerely. Which difference how great it is, let any man iudge.</p>
            <p>They do ſenſibly, manifeſtly, and palpably lie, when they ſay that our trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was leſſened by exceſſiue, and extraordinarie charges ſince the truce; ſeeing (beſide the paiment of many thouſands to the Frenchmen, vvhich were neither reckoned nor accounted, &amp; concerning which three yeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore &amp; alwaies after diuerſe demonſtrances were tendered in the Aſſembly of your Honours and Highneſſes) in the fines or mony-matters of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> there was no diſorder, &amp; no loſſe happened ſince the truce, but rather a great eaſe, and notable increaſe of things ſucceeded, as before I haue ſhewed. So that it was diligently prouided, that the debts and charges might not exceed the reuenewes.</p>
            <p>It is an apparant lie too, that I promiſed Preſident <hi>Ianyn,</hi> that in the while the truce laſt I would bring in the practiſe of the Romiſh religion: I alwaies laboured for the contrarie, ſo that the propounding thereof hitherto hath beene debarred, and kept heere in priuate.</p>
            <p>For theſe many yeeres I haue laboured with tooth and naile, priuately and publikely, to vnite all the companies of the Eaſt-Indies, &amp; make one generall one of them all, to procure the approbation, and aſſiſtance thereof. Which many of the companies thereof can witneſſe.</p>
            <p>And as ſoone as we may hope for a ſucceſſe of making a company for the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> I will beſtow my paines herein too, and confute thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:21782:28"/>
withſtand it. If theſe forgering fellowes would manifeſt and diſcouer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; maintaine what they haue written; I will vndertake to make good &amp; proue that in all other Articles, wherin they haue depoſed againſt me, they haue done me notable iniury: and that in many things they haue treſpaſſed againſt the authoritie, liberties, and priuiledges of the Countrey, and of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland;</hi> and that therefore both themſelues, as alſo they which had a hand in this buſineſſe, <note n="(a)">If they deſerue to bee puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, you deſerue death, by whoſe inſtigations theſe courſes were taken.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be ſeuerely puniſhed.</p>
            <p>When I would haue ended theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I thought with my ſelfe, and alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired your Honours, and Highneſſes in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and the Nobles and Gouernours of free-Cities in particular, to conſider, by <note n="(b)">The aſſertions following are meere impoſtures, deuiſed for <hi>Barneuelts</hi> protection, the ouerthrowe of <hi>Graue-Maurice,</hi> and the vtter deſtruction of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Therefore, reader, credite nothing therein. For my part, I will not make any ſtay in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring ſo much; but ſhowe it in a word, where need requires.</note> what meanes theſe tempeſts might bee allayed. In fine, I ſay (with reuerence and vnder your correction be it ſpoken) that all <note n="(c)">This crafts-maſter feares leſt hee ſhould bee called to an account for his doings, or rather conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereto. Wherefore for his owne ſaueguard hee perſwades that violence may be vſed vpon no man: the proofes hee vſes, are onely for faſhion ſake, and that vvith great words and titles hee may deterre vs from a further ſearching into the truth.</note> violent courſes (whereto the forenamed practiſes inclined) would bee hurtfull, and pernicious to the ſtate of the Prouinces and free Cities, to his Excellence, and his whole houſe, and euery member thereof, to all good Patriots of what condition ſoeuer, but eſpecially to the true and reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and all thoſe, who embrace it. And that that this was a meere plot deuiſed by the Spaniard to the perturbation, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ouerthrow and deſtruction, of theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Prouinces. Wherefore <note n="(d)">Marke how this bloud-ſucker heere makes way for future tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies: but his poiſon lies in his taile, take heed therefore of his venemous, and deadly ſting.</note> that ought to bee approued of, which the King of <hi>Frances</hi> Embaſſadour very diſcreetly, and with good reaſon commended, &amp; the King of <hi>England</hi> againe and againe counſelled and perſwaded both to the generall-States, and vnto you too in the yeere 1613. Whereto his Maieſties admonitions, and aduice giuen within this yeeres compaſſe may alſo bee referred, and applied: as alſo the counſell and admonitions of the King of <hi>Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Embaſſadour extraordinarie, and diuers warnings giuen to the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:21782:29"/>
purpoſe, in ſundry aſſemblies both publikely, and priuately. Namely, that all guile and diſſimulation, all ſiniſter ſuſpect, and ambition, all conceiued gall, hatred, and reuenge might be laid aſide, and the former grudges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forgotten, and not thought of (as farre as was poſſible without notable preiudice to any) a new vnitie of mindes might be made in charitie, peace and concord. For this is the onely remedy, whereby the counſels, hoſtilitie, and treacherie of the Spaniard might be reſiſted.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being done, ſpeciall care is to bee taken, that ſuch, as are deputed for the Aſſembly of the generall States, and thoſe, which conſult in common without any inſtructions, ſhould perſwade themſelues that the laſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricke</hi> vnion is the very foundation of their Aſſembly; well and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly prouiding, that the <note n="(a)">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yea, the thirteenth Article too? Ah!</hi> I' ay ſouuent ouy dire qu' on cognouit l'ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant au parler, &amp; le pot au ſonner.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>So gheſſe we at the metall by the ſound:</l>
                     <l>So by the voice, the beaſt in chaſe is found.</l>
                  </q>
               </note> Articles concluded of therein, as their prouidence and pleaſure thought fit, may be obſerued, and enacted; the defects of the former yeeres contributions may bee excuſed and ſupplied; Conſents may bee maturely and well obtained for the contributions of the yeere preſent, and ſatisfaction may be made vnto <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> by the contributions of the other ſeuerall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces proportionably for the money diſpended vpon two companies of footmen of the French, and two troopes of horſemen: That <note n="(b)">
                  <p>How ſtately doth hee heere like the principal commonwealthes man preſcribe lawes vnto the Generall States, and limit their power! and yet they are chiefe Lords, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators of all things. But if this Foxes cunning bee haply vnknowne to the Reader, I will briefely lay it open. <hi>Et à fin que ie ne te voye plus en ſiniſtre opinion de la choſe,</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>Regarde, car des yeux ie t' oſteray la nue,</l>
                        <l>Qui des yeux des humains rend moins clare Iauenë.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that you may no longer miſconceiue the matter:
<q>
                        <l>Attend, I meane the curtaine to vnfold,</l>
                        <l>Which yet the mindes cleere ſight in doubt doth hold.</l>
                     </q>
The prouinciall States beyond <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> and <hi>Vtricke</hi> (thoſe beyond the Iſlands now alſo are conformed by the moſt excellent Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> his meanes) are of the ancient Reformation, and theſe are the <hi>Gelderlanders,</hi> the <hi>Zutfeniens,</hi> the <hi>Zelanders,</hi> and <hi>Groenlanders:</hi> ſome belonging to theſe Prouinces are deputed to the <hi>Haighe,</hi> which make vp the Generall States. Who beeing, as I ſaid, of the ancient refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation for the moſt part, if they ſhould iudge <hi>Barneuelts</hi> cauſe, he were ſure to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. That this therefore may not come to paſſe, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelfe, he alwaies high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praiſes, commends, extols, exhorts, counſels the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> to whom this whole Apology is directed, <hi>viz.</hi> that they may countenance and defend his perſon, and not cauſe (for this is the mark he ſhootes at) nay, not ſuffer him to be drawn to a higher Tribunal; ſince all the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally are <hi>Arminians:</hi> The Reader vnderſtands mee. And to this purpoſe is that, which he addes concerning religion.</p>
               </note> the ſame Deputies take not cauſes in the foreſaid vnion into
<pb facs="tcp:21782:29"/>
their examination, and determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, either not committed vnto them, or expreſſely reſerued for particular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces by name; vnleſſe this be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them by the free conſent of the Prouinces iointly, all exacting of ſuffrages remoued: ſince this is to be accounted the vſurpation, and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the power and iuriſdiction of the ſeuerall Prouinces; whereof no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, but rather diſprofit and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may hereafter ariſe. That this <note n="(a)">That you may not pleaſe your ſelfe a whit herein; Mark mee: There the point in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is not concerning the <hi>Arminian</hi> Religion, but Romiſh Poperie: which if you would bring into requeſt againe; you goe againſt your oath, and that which you formerly auerred touching the Gouernour <hi>Iauyn.</hi> And truely if the <hi>Vtricke</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion be to bee kept, as you vrge, then all Papists will tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, who may freely then ſay all their Maſſes. Yea, if the thirteenth Article ought to be obſerued, all Monkes are to bee called backe againe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the confederated Prouinces, all Eccleſiaſticall goods and Monaſteries are to be reſtored. Let my Lords the States marke, whither hee and his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſme comes. Are theſe Spaniſh Counſels, and the ſtirrings vp of ſleeping Wolues?</note> is moſt fitting in cauſes concerning Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is manifeſt by the expreſſe text of the aforeſaid Vnion, and alſo by diuers other Treaties; namely, that the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining concerning Religion, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thereto appertaining, is reſerued to each ſeuerall Prouince:<note n="(b)">I will ſpeake plainely, you lie.</note> and the cuſtome obſerued for theſe thirtie yeeres laſt paſt in the foreſaid aſſemblies, was agreeable hereto, ſo that herein nothing at all was done without the ioynt-conſent of all the Prouinces.</p>
            <p>That his <note n="(c)">
                  <hi>Mauritius</hi> knowes what the Anagram of his name imports. <hi>Mars viuit.</hi> Noble Prince, let him feele and haue experiment of your power and valour: cleere your ſelfe, and your honour.</note> Excellencie, and the Councell of the State in ordering the affaires of the State, and of the warre
<pb facs="tcp:21782:30"/>
belonging to the Prouinces in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, doe follow the Inſtructions, which the Lords the generall States vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mature deliberation ſhall giue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame: and which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues interchangeably haue confirmed by oath, that they will follow, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue. And that it ſhould be ſo prouided that the Prouinces might purge, and ſupply and make good their former defaults in giuing their conſents; and each of them, for their particular, keepe <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland</hi> ſcot-free and harmeleſſe concerning the expenſes which the French horſemen and ſouldiers with their Officers put them to: and further that good order might be taken for the yeerely contributions and paiment thereof, and that the charges may not farre exceed the receiued contributions: and that care bee taken, that nothing be done in matters of greater importance without the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, and knowledge of the generall States: that nothing be attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted contrarie to the liberties, rights, priuiledges, and cuſtomes of the Prouinces, free-cities &amp; members thereof: and particularly that there be no let, &amp; hinderance, concerning the performance of the two &amp; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith Article of the foreſaid inſtruction, for very weighty cauſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained. That his Excellence, and the Companies of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miraltie, order the affaires, and proceedings of the warre by Sea, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meanes with their appurtenances, preſcribed by the ſaid inſtruction, which alſo they promiſed by oath: and that in bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes extraordinarie, and of more moment, they proceede not vvithout the notice and conſent of the States generall, foreſeeing withall that the charges ſurpaſſe not too much the reuenewes and Incomes.</p>
            <p>The Gentrie, Nobles, and Deputies of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> argue not about any inſtruction, but conſent vnto the Articles propoſed, or refuſed, and are bound to ſpeake their opinion in all chances for the benefite and ſecuritie as well of the Prouinces in generall, as alſo of the members and cities thereof in particular. Wherein chiefely muſt bee regarded the vnion made betwixt the members &amp; cities firſt of all, and then betwixt euery particular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, conſidering for what end the members and cities were inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably conioined, and therein ſhowing the ancient truth and
<pb facs="tcp:21782:30"/>
honeſtie, with their ſincere agreement, and aſſured confidence in the one and other: A forgetfulneſſe caſt ouer things paſt for the good of the Prouinces, members, and cities thereof. In the cauſe of Religion a toleration would be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a <note n="(a)">How long ſhall this time be? as long as <hi>Barneuelt</hi> liues? or till <hi>Temothah.</hi> I ſpeake vnto my brethren in a dialect, which they onely vnderſtand: <hi>raſcag, raga, reſoneet ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic ieſcamu?</hi> It were too long. Some ſpeedier courſe muſt be taken; becauſe <hi>chone malach, Adonai ſauif lireau vai hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letſem;</hi> and becauſe <hi>pene le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah begoſerag, lehach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rith meerets zicram.</hi> One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let them performe it coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly.</note> time, &amp; an agreement made with thoſe, who are otherwiſe minded concerning the point of Predeſtination, and the appendices thereof: all other in conueniences in the meane time preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and in other matters a continuance in the reformed doctrine granted. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, an Eccleſiaſticall Decree muſt bee made, and the Eccleſiaſticall ſocietie, and diſcipline reſtored according to the tenour thereof: From henceforth <note n="(a)">How fearefull he is of himſelfe? but his puniſhment now drawes neere.</note> keeping their promiſes and decrees, that no man bee demanded, ſifted, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for his Religion, or opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame: that euery one may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely liue in peace and quietneſſe vnder the lawfull gouernement of theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces and Cities. And in caſe the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid opinions muſt needs be decided, then without partakings, &amp; according to reaſon it be enquired, &amp; by what way, order, and meeting, that may beſt bee done by the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>That his Excellence, and the Senators deputed by you deale in all affaires of the State, in Eccleſiaſtical and <note n="(bb)">
                  <p>Noble Gentleman, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince, giue this coward the hearing, but follow not his counſell.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Labori eux Athlete, &amp; pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreux d'exercice,</l>
                     <l>Qui ne trembla iamais pour un petit novice.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And howſoeuer you haue dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to cope with your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, <hi>deſſous un fer rouille n' eſt moins preux un Achille.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> ſecular gouernment, in the warres belonging vnto the Prouinces of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friſland,</hi> the members and Cities thereof, ſpecially according to their ſeuerall commiſſions, inſtructions, reſolutions, and Actes; and that in great and weighty matters your conſent bee ſought for, and that in all things your decrees be obſerued. <note n="(bb)">
                  <p>Noble Gentleman, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince, giue this coward the hearing, but follow not his counſell.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Labori eux Athlete, &amp; pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreux d'exercice,</l>
                     <l>Qui ne trembla iamais pour un petit novice.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And howſoeuer you haue dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to cope with your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, <hi>deſſous un fer rouille n' eſt moins preux un Achille.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> That his Excellence and the Iudges in caſes iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall, and other differences may equally adminiſter Iuſtice, and bee aſſiſted for
<pb facs="tcp:21782:31"/>
the better performance thereof.</p>
            <p>That the Exchequer in guiding the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and other matters left to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall thereof, duely execute it office, and be encouraged in execution thereof.</p>
            <p>That the Officers both in general and particular, and all gouernours of Citie: and Townes behaue themſelues decently in promoting a good and ciuill gouernement, in the Adminiſtration of Iuſtice, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the publike good; and in a word, in procuring the peace and vnitie of Cities, Boroughs, ſtrangers, and towne-dwellers, that they wiſely vſe their authoritie, and be aſſiſted and confirmed in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe things bee thus ordered, and euery one haue their owne right, if euery ones <note n="(a)">How gladly would hee bee a great Lord and Maſter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all? but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But there is a God that ſees and ſurely puniſhes ſuch things.</note> authoritie, office, honour, and poſſeſſions be reſerued to themſelues ſafe and ſound, without doubt within a ſhort time al things wil go better with vs.</p>
            <p>My good Lords, I haue beene more <note n="(b)">So haue my caſtigations: therefore if you obtaine pardon, I haue no reaſon to deſpayre of it, for in tediouſneſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixitie we iu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe: only your cauſe vs worſe then mine, for the truth is ſtrong aboue al things, and conquereth for euermore.</note> tedious, then I was aware of: I intreat you all to looke to marters as well gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally as particularly concerning your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues, rights, priuiledges and ſafetie. For <note n="(c)">
                  <p>And heere thus agained.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Souvent i'ay beu, encor qu' a contre oeur,</l>
                     <l>Quand i' auoy mal, de tres amers breuvages.</l>
                     <l>O Socij, neque enim ignari ſumus ante malorum;</l>
                     <l>O paſſi grauiora: dabit De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us his quoque finem.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Thoſe are not the firſt euils (I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wis) we haue endured: &amp; we hope, braue mates, to bee rid of theſe.</p>
               </note> my part, ſuch were my troubles (yet God deliuered me out of them) in the yeares 1586, and 1587, vnder the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and in the yeares 1588, 1589 vnder the Lord Willoughby, his ſucceſſour in the gouernment of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh garriſons (vnder whoſe name theſe impudent forgers ſeeke to ſhelter &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage themſelues) then in the yeare 1600 after the battell of <hi>Flanders,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the yeare 1608. in the treaty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the league: For theſe 32. yeares the truth hath triumphed in her conqueſt ouer falſhood. I preſume, <note n="(d)">Amen, Amen, may God aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yle the the truth and her followers: but you and your wicked ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, your <hi>Arminians,</hi> ſlaues to Antichriſt, ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh together. For thus much I preſume except you repent, and conforme yourſelfe to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</note> God in his
<pb facs="tcp:21782:31"/>
good time will aſſoile the truth, deſtroy falſhood, and confound the authours thereof: and others alſo there are (and thoſe great ones and of good deſerts too) not onely in our Prouinces, but in the neighbour kingdoms alſo &amp; dominions, as well heretofore, as in this preſent age, who could not acquit &amp; free themſelues from ſuch &amp; greater calumnies &amp; falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations. I <note n="(a)">And I moſt mighty God, earneſtly beſeech thee, from the ſupreame Throne of thy Maieſty, that thou wouldſt bee pleaſed to looke vpon thy holy People, and the faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of thy Church: and ſo fortifie, protect, and defend them againſt their inſulting enemies whereſoeuer, the falſe brethren and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and eſpecially the maintayners of the <hi>Arminian</hi> wicked ſect, who ſeeke to trouble and breake that vnion which thou haſt confirmed; That they whom thou haſt praedeſtinated to ſaluation, may alwayes haue the vpper hand, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the certainty of their ſaluation: but they, whom thou haſt created vnto confuſion, and as veſſels of thy moſt iuſt wrath, may tumble and be thruſt head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long thither, whereto from all eternitie thou didſt predeſtinate them, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had done any good or euil. Euen ſo Father, becauſe it ſeemed good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: thy word is truth, thy word endures for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </note> beſeech Almightie God in mercie to open your eyes, (my good Lords) and with the bleſſing of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly grace to ſtrengthen and confirme you in your proſperous and happy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From the Haigh, <date>April 20. 1618.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
